<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the behaviour of the fourteen late popish malefactors whil'st in Newgate and their discourses with the Ordinary ... : also a confutation of their appeals, courage, and cheerfulness at execution / by Samuel Smith ...</title>
            <author>Smith, Samuel, 1620-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60546</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10786</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13293216</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13293216</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98865</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60546)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98865)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 439:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the behaviour of the fourteen late popish malefactors whil'st in Newgate and their discourses with the Ordinary ... : also a confutation of their appeals, courage, and cheerfulness at execution / by Samuel Smith ...</title>
                  <author>Smith, Samuel, 1620-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst, Dorman Newman, Tho. Cockeril, and Tho. Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98865:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98865:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT, OF THE Behaviour of the Fourteen <hi>Late Popiſh Malefactors,</hi> whil'ſt in <hi>NEWGATE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Their Diſcourſes with the Ordinary, VIZ.
<list>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Staley,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Grove,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Pickering,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Green,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Berry,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Whitebread,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Harcourt,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Fenwick,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Gawen,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Turner,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>AND</item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Langhorn.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO, A <hi>CONF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TATION</hi> of their Appeals, Courage, and Cheerfulneſs, at <hi>Execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>SAMUEL SMITH,</hi> Ordinary of <hi>Newgate,</hi> and Miniſter of the GOSPEL.</p>
            <q>He who is Firſt in his Own Cauſe, ſeemes Juſt; But his Neighbor comes, and Searches him,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 18.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>It is not probable, that ſuch who will Perjure themſelves, to Calunmiate Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, ſhould be Capable of giving any real Teſtimonies for Themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt, Dorman Newman, Tho. Cockeril,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Simmons,</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98865:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98865:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Unmasking of the Thirteen Popiſh Malefactors: AND Their Diſcourſes with the Ordinary, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>IT being deſired of me by a Worthy Divine, that I ſhould Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh what I ſaid to <hi>Staley,</hi> who was Condemn'd for Treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Speeches: Likewiſe my Diſcourſes with the other Twelve Jeſuitical and Popiſh Conſpirators, before their being Drawn out to their Execution: I could not (though with ſome reluctancy at firſt) but grant him his Requeſt; hoping that this Narrative may be of publick Uſe and Benefit to all, into whoſe hands it ſhall come; to acquaint them with the Truth of what I ſpake to them, by way of Advice, to Prepare them for their approaching Death: And that I may give ſome Satisfaction, to ſuch as are apt to be ſtaggered in the Belief of their Abominable Crimes, becauſe they frequently Avowed their Innocency. Which Satisfaction I ſhall perform in order as they Suffered.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I. Mr. <hi>Staley.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe firſt perſon Executed, was Mr. <hi>Staley,</hi> who ſpake Treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable words againſt his Majeſty, which expreſly threatned to take away his Sacred Life. I did frequently, after the Sentence of Death was paſt on the ſaid <hi>Staley,</hi> viſit him in order to Prepare him for his Execution. In my firſt Addreſs to him, I told him, I came not to inſult over him, but out of Conſcience to diſcharge the Duty of my Office: He received me with great wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs, and ſaid, <hi>He had great Terror upon his Conſcience for the Guilt of his many and great Sins;</hi> yet utterly deny'd the ſpeaking of thoſe words for which he ſtood Condemned. I told him, that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt way to be free from thoſe Terrors, was to make an Ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Penitent acknowledgement; and that for Tongue-ſins or ſecret Heart-ſins formerly Indulged, God might juſtly deſert him, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare himſelf by ſuch Treaſonable Words. He ſaid, <hi>He never had any thought of miſchief againſt the Kings Perſon.</hi> I replied, that words were the natural product of thoughts, and a frequent Prologue to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98865:3"/>the moſt abominable Actions. He perſiſted in denying, that he ſpoke any words tending to that ſenſe; but when I told him, that his friend, who was Drinking with him, could, or had Depoſed upon Oath, that he ſpake thoſe very words: He replied, <hi>Nay, if my Friend will ſware ſo much, it is probable I might (in the heat and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy of Paſſion) utter them, though they never were intended in my Heart.</hi> He had great Remorſe for the ſinfulneſs of his. Life, and expreſſed ſome particulars which I ſhall not mention. I told him, if he expected any ſettlement of true ſerenity in Conſcience, that he muſt not ſeek it in adhering to the <hi>Romiſh Religion;</hi> For falſe and looſe Principles can never produce ſolid and laſting Comfort: then I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to convince him from the Sacred Scriptures, of the many Abſurdities which are maintain'd by Popiſh Doctors, that it is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption not to doubt of Salvation, and yet that a perſon may Merit it, which is utterly inconſiſtent; for if any man doubt of his future happy eſtate, how can he Merit it? and if he may Merit it, what need he doubt, when by works of a ſelf-Righteouſneſs, he can create a Title, or may lay Claim to Eternal Life? I judged it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, in order to the removing his Terror in Conſcience, to inform him aright; that although it were impoſſible to fulfil the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works, or to attain any Perfection in this Life; yet there is a Foundation of hope, for degenerate Man-kind as reſtored to the Image of God by Chriſt; Whoſe ſatisfaction to divine Juſtice, is of infinit value and vertue: ſo that Chriſt being the only Mediator by Redemption, it is Blaſphemy, and the higheſt Sacriledg to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute or invocate any Saint or Angel as a Mediator of interceſſion. For this is equivalent to Chriſt's Infinit Satisfaction, as grounding the Right of his interceſſion, eſpecially conſidering, that Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atory Interceſſion is only the repreſenting and pleading the Merit of infinit Satisfaction. Upon this, he expreſt an Aſſent to what I had affirmed, by bowing his head; and applying his hand to his Breaſt, he ſaid, <hi>Sir, Go on.</hi> Then I unfolded the nature and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Faith and Repentance in order to the Juſtification of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; how they were the conditions of the Covenant of Grace, So required of us, for pardon of ſin, and eternal Life; As that they could not be extracted out of the power of free-will in man, but were the ſole purchaſe of Chriſts free-Love; who by his Spirit, infuſing the principle of Faith and Repentance, doth Regenerate, and actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reconcile a ſinner to God; and ſo Redeem, or ſet him free from the ſlavery of his corrupt will, which he cannot ſhake off by any Improvement of Natural Reaſon, or moral Reſolutions. I ſtated alſo the difference twixt true ſaving faith and repentance, from that which is falſe: And that the Office of Faith, is not only to rely on
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98865:3"/>the mercy of God, and merits of Chriſt, but alſo to give back the the whole man, in an hearty reſignation, to the conduct and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Chriſts Word and Spirit in all things. That Saving-Repentance was not an Act of meer Attrition, which only effects a legal conſternation in Conſcience, from the apprehenſion of guilt, and divine Wrath: But true Repentance is Evangelical, wrought deep in the heart by ſound Contrition for ſin as ſin, chiefly for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the Holy God: ſo that it is the reſult of an holy filial In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, and is incouraged by the hope of Mercy, attended with an hatred of all ſin, and a ſtudious reſolution to walk in all holy Obedience. Here I told him, what an unſound dangerous Opinion that was of the <hi>Romiſh Doctors,</hi> who maintain Attrition only with the receit of the Euchariſt, and the Sacrament of Abſolution at the very point of Death to be a ſufficient Paſport for a comfortable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it out of the World, or Ticket to claime Salvation: After this, and ſome other Diſcourſe, he thankt me for my Advice, and ſaid, <hi>He was much Benefited, Supported, and Comforted thereby:</hi> And deſired me, as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently as I could, to renew my viſits of him; ſo I promiſed I would, and then I prayd with him; and he was very intentive, and much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with what I Pray'd.</p>
                  <p>When I came again, he complained, that his heart was not ſo throughly Contrite for ſin as he deſired; that he was much perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that he had no more Aſſurance of a future happy ſtate. I ſtated the nature of true ſaving-Faith, that it was an adherence to the free grace of God in Chriſt, for pardon and Eternal Life, joyned with an obedient ſelf-reſignation; and where this was wrought, the ſoul-ſtate was ſafe, tho aſſurance of Gods Love might be wanting. For this was not an eſſential Priviledge, abſolutely neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but only a peculiar favor given to ſtrict walking Chriſtians; and that only at ſome ſet-times, in great extremity and need of ſuch hidden <hi>Manna.</hi> That it was rather of the nature of a Rational ſhort ſenſation, than the Ground of ſetled Comfort; which is the reſult of an Heroical ſtrain of Faith, to truſt in God, when he ſeems to reject and ſlay us; and that the Lord doth more eſteem this reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute dependency, in the midſt of ſeeming-contradictions, than the moſt multiplyed Acts of external Worſhip. Upon this he was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more ſerene in his mind: And I told him, that in praying and ſeeking the Lord more fervently, comfort would gradually be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
                  <p>The next day he diſtruſted his Heart, as to the Truth of his Faith and Repentance, which I told him, was a good ſigne that he was in a hopeful way of making his Peace with God. That he muſt wait in believing that he ſhould obtain Comfort promiſed to the Penitent.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98865:4"/>He deſired me to pray with him, and for him; and to prepare to ſpeak ſomwhat of the ſufferings of Chriſt, when I ſhould next Viſit him. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, from that Text, <hi>I am Crucified with Chriſt,</hi> I treated of many parts of his Bitter Paſſion, and of his Soul-agonies, inferring matter not only of Comfort from thence, but alſo of Inſtruction, for our Imitation and Conformity. I left him afterward in a frame more willing and fit to Die; and comming to him on the very Morning he was to Suffer, he told me, that <hi>Now he had more Comfort, and an hope of his future Happy-ſtate:</hi> yet renouncing all opinion of worth in his own Tears, Prayers, and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation. He was ſolicitous, if the Executioner ſhould deal with him according to the ſtrictneſs of the Sentence, leſt feeling any pain (if Cut down, &amp; ript up Alive) he ſhould Curſe, or uſe any Unchriſtian word: <hi>Which rather than to do</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I would Bite my Tongue in pieces; for I dread Sin now, more than Death.</hi> I told him, that I hoped the manner of his Execution would be mitigated; however, that God would prevent Sin in him at the time of his Suffering, becauſe he was ſo anxious as to diſtruſt himſelf, and cautious to avoid all unbecomming Words or Geſtures. After ſome farther Diſcourſe, I pray'd with him, and he was much pleaſed with my attendance about him; yet he ſpared me from going with him to the place of Execution for ſome Reaſons. I cannot ſay how he declared himſelf there, becauſe I was not preſent: But upon my whole Obſervation of his Behaviour in Priſon, I do charitably judge, he was a real Penitentiary. It was doubtful to ſome, whether he dyed in the <hi>Roman</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> becauſe (as I think) he did not at laſt declare himſelf either way: Yet this I am ſure of, that if he had ſolid and true Comfort in Dying, this could not proceed from ſuch a ſandy foundation as his old Popiſh Principles, but only from Self-abhorrency in the ſenſe of his great Sinfulneſs, and the defectiveneſs of his beſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> that he might build his hope on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> only, as the <hi>Rock</hi> of Eternal Life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>II. Mr. <hi>Coleman.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Come now to <hi>Coleman,</hi> of whom I can ſay very little, becauſe he had an Arrogant opinion of his own Abilities; and out of an Hope to be Canonized for a Saint, deſpiſed and rejected any Aſſiſtance from me, either by Diſcourſe or Prayer. I offered him both on the next day after the Sentence of Death paſs'd upon him; but he returned me this Anſwer (by the Meſſenger I ſent to him, to know if he would admit me) <hi>That he had but a very ſhort time to Prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for Death, and would not be hindred in the Loſs of any part of it;</hi> thanking me for my offer of Viſiting him, but deſired me to forbear. I put a fair conſtruction on the Meſſage brought me at the firſt, thinking he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98865:4"/>might be very buſie at that time, about ſome extraordinary em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ergency, or indiſpoſed to be Viſited; and therefore told the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, that I would attend on him on ſome other fit time. The Officer told me, that Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> would never admit me; and he inferred it from his manner of ſpeaking that Meſſage which he ſent by him; he obſerved his Countenance and Geſtures in the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of it. So I totally deſiſted. Yet when he was brought down from his Chamber in the <hi>Preſs-yard</hi>-ſide, to go to the Sledge, I ſtayed him a little, ſaying, Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> You did not think well of admitting me, yet know, I have earneſtly Prayed that God would give you true and great Repentance for your great Crimes, ſtand not out in your denying of them. Some other words I uſed, to which he replyed in ſhort and quick tone, <hi>Thank you, thank you.</hi> As I moved nearer with him towards the gate, he ſaid, <hi>Sir, I muſt beg your Pardon.</hi> It being a ſtrange word to drop from Him, I askt him for what? He replyed, <hi>That I did not Admit you; but truly, it was not in any contempt of your Office; but when you ſent to me, I was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome perplexed Thoughts; and for other Conſideratious, thought it not Convenient.</hi> Then I told him, that I would pray for him as a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man, which he took well, and ſo we parted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III. Mr. <hi>Grove.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MR. <hi>Grove</hi> was Executed on Friday the 24th. of <hi>January</hi> 1678. I ſpake to him in the Chappel theſe words (before he was carried down the Stone-ſtairs unto the Sledg:) Sir, I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire you, Now that you are going to appear at the Tribunal of Chriſt, that you would clear your Conſcience and ſpeak the Truth, that you may die in Peace: And I do Exhort you, that you would beg of God great Repentance for your great ſins. He repli'd, <hi>That he did underſtand his Duty.</hi> Yet I perſiſted, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort him not to truſt to the merits of any Saint or Angel, but whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to go out of himſelf, not grounding any Confidence of his Salvation on any prayers, tears, nor the deepeſt Humiliation of his own heart. That even Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaid, when dying, <hi>It was ſafeſt to rely wholly and ſolely on the Alſufficient Merits of the bleſſed</hi> Jeſus. Mr. <hi>Grove</hi> replied, <hi>That Thomas a Kempis had ſaid the ſame:</hi> To which I replied, Do you conſider of it, and Act accordingly: For you muſt not hazard your Souls eternal welfare by any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptious mixing of your own good works with Chriſts Infinit Satisfaction and Merits. For the Apoſtle ſaint <hi>Paid</hi> ſaith, <hi>If Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication be of Works, it is altogether of Works; but if of free Grace, it is altogether of Grace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98865:5"/>
                  <p>So I took leave of Mr. <hi>Grove,</hi> deſiring him to conſider well of what I had ſaid, Praying that the Lord would in much mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy look upon his ſoul to pardon him, and fit him for his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Death. Mr. <hi>Grove</hi> ſeemed to take in good part what was ſaid to him. After which, he was conducted down to the Sledg.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>IV. Mr. <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MR. <hi>Ireland</hi> was Executed on the ſame day with Mr. <hi>Grove,</hi> to whom I had not time to ſay more than theſe few words, <hi>viz.</hi> Sir, I do earneſtly beg of God to grant you mercy and pardon for your great ſins. Truſt alone in the Righteouſneſs and Merits of Chriſt Jeſus: Compoſe your ſelf in your paſſage, and ſix your Heart upon the Lord, till you Expire. Which words Mr. <hi>Ireland</hi> ſeemed to take kindly from me: And ſo we took leave of each other.</p>
                  <p>Here I cannot forbear to give ſome account of Mr. <hi>Irelands</hi> perverting of a Woman who was Burnt in <hi>Smithfield</hi> for Clipping his Majeſties Coine. This ſeduction of the ſaid Woman from the Proteſtant Religion, was before Mr. <hi>Ireland</hi> was Apprehended for the late Conſpiracy. An Officer in <hi>Newgate</hi> did aſſure me, when <hi>Ireland</hi> was committed for the Plot, that he was able to take his Oath, that <hi>Ireland</hi> perverted that woman ſome time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; for he well knew him upon a ſecond Reveiw, but knew him not to be a <hi>Papiſt</hi> or <hi>Prieſt</hi> at firſt; for he was admitted to her as a Friend. <hi>Irelands</hi> ſtratagem in turning the Woman to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> was thus diſcovered. Early on the morning on which ſhe was Executed, I askt her, what hope ſhe had of a future happy ſtate? ſhe hufft at me, telling me, <hi>I need not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my ſelf about her, for ſhe was ſure of her Salvation.</hi> I wondered at her Confidence, but ſuſpected not the Grounds of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepartneſs.</p>
                  <p>After I had Exhorted and Prayed with her at the place of Execution, and was taking my farewell of her; ſhe entreated me to give her ſome time to pray for her ſelf, which ſhe did: In her Prayer, ſhe mixed theſe words, <hi>Lord grant, that the offering up of my Body to the Flames, may expiate the guilt of all my Sins, and ſave my ſoul.</hi> I told her, when ſhe had finiſht her prayer, that the foreſaid expreſſion ſmelt rank of <hi>Popery;</hi> and therefore askt her, what Religion ſhe came to die in? She replied, <hi>ſhe was a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick.</hi> I askt her, How long ſhe had been ſuch? She ſaid, <hi>that a good Miniſter had told her, that if ſhe died in the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98865:5"/>ſhe was ſure to be Damned.</hi> And that he proved it by this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and upon this Rock will I Build my Church.</hi> So that, he aſſur'd her, that the Religion of the <hi>Romiſh Biſhop,</hi> who was St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor, was the <hi>Rock</hi> there meant; and ſo there was no Salvation to thoſe who are Separatiſts from that Church, and the Profeſſion of it. I told her, That the <hi>Prieſt</hi> had deceived her. For the <hi>Rock</hi> was not St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Perſon, nor his Verbal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for if ſo, Where was the <hi>Rock,</hi> and, What be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of the <hi>Church,</hi> when St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſo ſhamefully denyed his <hi>Lord</hi> thrice? But the only True <hi>Rock,</hi> on which the Church is Built, is the very Perſon, Offices and Merits of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Son of <hi>God,</hi> who was the Object of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Confeſſion. She was attentive to what I ſaid, and ſeemed ſomewhat ſenſible of her being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. Saying, <hi>She was willing to be Saved betwixt us Both.</hi> But I told her, She muſt not halt 'twixt two Religions, ſo oppoſite to each other; and that it was very dangerous to dye in the <hi>Roman</hi> Perſwaſion. She told me, <hi>She could not Renounce it, in as much as the ſaid</hi> Prieſt <hi>had obliged her by the Bleſſed Sacrament, that ſhe ſhould never recant or depart from the</hi> Popiſh Religion, <hi>as the beſt and ſafeſt to Dye in.</hi> I convinced her with Arguments to the contrary; yea, ſhe her ſelf was not Credulous of their abſurd Affirming of the <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> of the Sacramental Bread and Wine, into the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Body and Blood of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> For ſhe ſaid, <hi>She neither taſted any Fleſh or Blood.</hi> She alſo declared, <hi>That ſhe had no Good Works of her own, which ſhe durſt truſt to, as Meritorious of Heaven; but relyed whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſolely on Chriſt's Righteouſneſs.</hi> Whereupon I told her, She deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the grand Points of <hi>Popery;</hi> and therefore, was a <hi>Papiſt</hi> to get a Pretended Abſolution, or upon ſome Deſigne. But, fearing to Dye in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Opinions, ſhe ask't me, <hi>If ſhe ſhould not be Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured, if ſhe renounced them, having taken the Sacrament, to perſiſt in them?</hi> I told her, That ſhe muſt not cleave to an unlawful wicked Oath; but beg Repentance of God, that ſhe ſo eaſily ſuffered her ſelf to be ſeduced. I told her, That the Lord ſaith by the Prophet, <hi>That an Oath muſt be taken in Truth, Righteouſneſs, and Judgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, ſhe did not, neither could ſwear in Truth, becauſe it was to a Falſe Religion; nor in Judgment, in Wiſdom and Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe ſhe ſwore raſhly and inconſiderately: Therefore, this Oath was Void in its own Nature; and it could not bind her, the Matter of it being Unlawful and Wicked.</p>
                  <p>At laſt, being Convinced of her Error, ſhe was willing to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract it: But I told her, That what ſhe did, ſhe muſt do willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and from a ſincere penitent Frame of Heart. She ſaid, <hi>She could and would freely</hi> (out of Conviction of her Duty) <hi>Renounce all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98865:6"/>Romiſh Opinions and Practices;</hi> which ſhe did openly, with an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Voice; affirming, That ſhe dyed a <hi>True Proteſtant.</hi> So I took her by the Hand, and Prayed again with her, that God would par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don her former Levity, and give her Perſeverance in the True Faith, which ſhe had ſo ſolemnly re-imbraced.</p>
                  <p>This was the firſt Diſcovery of Proſelyting condemned Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors at <hi>Newgate:</hi> To prevent which Seduction, Captain <hi>Richard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> (ſince this came to his Knowledge) is very watchful, and gives all his Officers a Charge to ſuffer none to come to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Perſons, but only ſuch whom they know to be <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant-Divines;</hi> and that alwayes, an Officer be preſent to hear what paſſes in Diſcourſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>V. Mr. <hi>Pickering.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Had diſcourſe with him before his Execution; but he would not permit me to pray with him, only deſired my Prayers at Home for him; which I promiſed him, and he Thanked me. I was preſent at his Execution, becauſe he was Hanged after three other ordinary Malefactors. When he came out of the Sledge into the Cart, He had a great Fluſhing in his Face; I apprehended by his Words and Geſture, that he had Elevated his Artificial Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; or rather ſunck himſelf into a Sullenneſs, by taking Cordyal-Spirits: For he was unconcerned at the Approach of his own Death, and no way affected with his monſtrous Crime. With an impudent Face, a lying Tongue, and anticke Carriage, he Denyed what he was Condemned for, and Aſſerted his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency. He was reproved by the Sheriffs, for ſuch impudent Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; having had a fair Tryal, and found Guilty of the whole Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment charged upon him: Yet ſo ſeared are the Conſciences of theſe Grand Traytors, and Enemies to all Order, and well-Eſtabliſh't Government, as well as the True and Pure Religion, that they will hazard the Eternal Loſs of their Souls, as to a future hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py State, rather than declare any Remorſe for their abominable Deſignes and Practices. Yea, they ſtick not to juſtify themſelves, as if Perjury could change the heinous Nature of Treaſon, and waſh it into a perfect Innocency.</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Richard How</hi> told <hi>Pickering,</hi> That he ſhould have a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Time to prepare for his inſtant Death, if he would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it well, and not miſpend it in extravagant, and falſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. He likewiſe call'd unto him, to put him in mind of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for himſelf; alleading, that it was reported, that he was a <hi>Prieſt;</hi> therefore, he ought to be able to pray, in Expreſſions, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98865:6"/>with Affections ſuitable to his preſent Diſtreſs: Yet <hi>Pickering</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther warned the People, to take heed of an ill Life, nor Confeſs'd any Sin to God, of which himſelf was Guilty; but with a kind of rude ſmiling, denyed himſelf to be a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> but only a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Brother. Sir <hi>Richard</hi> ask't him, If he were aſhamed of his Religion, or, That the People ſhould hear him Pray? For ſome of his Fraternity, Executed before, only muttered a few Private <hi>Ave-Maryes,</hi> or other <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prayers, to themſelves. Then <hi>Pickering</hi> repeated the <hi>Lord's-Prayer,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtolical-Creed;</hi> and ſaid no more, as to any Religious Concernments. Then the <hi>Ordinary,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Cart with him, exhorted him to Expreſs himſelf more fully and pathetically in Prayer, ſutable to the diſtreſs of a Dying Man, which he refuſed to do. Then I ask't him, that I might Pray for him, becauſe he might be uncompoſed or indiſpoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: But he ſaid, That he did not matter it; he had rather I ſhould let it alone. So after a ſtrange unbecoming, ſtupid, and ſullen behaviour of himſelf, when he deſired no longer time, his face was vailed, and he was turned off: he hung about half an hour, and then was Cut down and Quartered.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>VI. Mr. <hi>Green.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GReen</hi> was one of the Murtherers of Sir <hi>Edmundberry Godfrey.</hi> He was born in <hi>Ireland</hi> of a Proteſtant Father, (as himſelf ſaid) but his mother being a Papiſt and his father dying, she com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Son to his Uncle (her brother) for Education, in the Popish Religon. <hi>Green</hi> could neither read nor write, yet his Uncle had ſo trained him up in the Popish Principles, that he was a fitter ſubject (when grown up) for Popish Prieſts to work upon, and make him an Engine for their deſtructive Practiſes. This appeared by their inveigling of him into the horrid murther of the ſaid Sir <hi>Edmund: Green</hi> had ſome time before been prefer'd to be Chappel-keeper at <hi>Sommerſet</hi>-houſe. Hereupon the chief contrivers of that Murther, took their opportunity to draw him in, to be an Actor in that bloody Tragedy. <hi>Green</hi> was very ready at hand for that purpoſe, and was the eaſier induced thereunto, becauſe Sir <hi>Edmund,</hi> being one of his Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace, was very active in diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and committing Popiſh Prieſts to Cuſtody: his Life was laid wait for ſeveral times, not only for the reaſon aforeſaid, but chiefly becauſe he had taken ſome Examinations upon Oath, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the late Horrid popiſh Conſpiracy, which they thought (if Sir <hi>Edmund</hi> were kill'd) would be loſt, or not ſo valid in their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibility. But in this they were infatuated, for the murther of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98865:7"/>this Worthy Patriot, confirmed the belief of the Plot. The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of contriving Sir <hi>Edmund</hi>'s Death was thus. As he paſſed by <hi>Sommerſet</hi>-Houſe, he was importun'd by ſome of the Complices in the murthering of him, to turn in at the Gate, under pretence that there was a fray within the Court; and that he being a Juſtice of the Peace, might (as he was bound) do a great good Office in appeaſing the Scuffle. Sir <hi>Edmund</hi> went in, not miſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their deſign on him: But theſe cruel Enemies to the Proteſtant Religion, had no ſooner got him into the back part of <hi>Sommer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi>-Houſe, but they joſled him into a private room, and there ſet upon him with their Fury. The Narrative is in Print, and too tedious to relate. Therefore in ſum, as to <hi>Greens</hi> part, who acted in that bloody Tragedy, it was proved upon Oath, that he ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Sir <hi>Edmund;</hi> and farther acted, in conveighing his dead body to the place where it was afterwards found. <hi>Green</hi> being condemned to be hanged for this Barbarous Murther, I proffer'd my ſelf (as <hi>Ordinary</hi>) to viſit, and fit him for his approaching Death. He accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of it, and I went to him ſeveral days, to make him ſenſible of ſo great a Crime. He ſtifly denied it, as alſo did <hi>Hill</hi> and <hi>Berry,</hi> to the laſt. I urged <hi>Green</hi> with various Arguments, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the Soveraignty of divine Providence, which had thus won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully brought to light ſuch a ſecret miſtery of Iniquity, hardly to be parallell'd, in any Age. Yet <hi>Green</hi> was very obſtinate, in ſtanding out to deny, that he knew any thing of this Murther more or leſs, which I told him proceeded from ſome or all of theſe Reaſons following; either becauſe he had taken an Oath of Secreſy, or counted it no ſin, but rather a meritorious Act, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſuch a grand Heretick as Sir <hi>Edmund</hi> was accounted. Or had received a Popiſh Abſolution from the Guilt of that Murther, and ſo lookt upon himſelf as Innocent as the Child Unborn. Or would not confeſs that horrid Crime, to decline caſting a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach upon the Popiſh Party. Yet however, I did not ceaſe for many days to exhort him, to unburthen his <hi>Conſcience</hi> of this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Guilt. I aggravated in many particulars, the heinouſneſs of the ſin of Murther, eſpecially of this, committed with ſuch perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and cruel Circumſtances. Yet no Arguments prevailed with him to acknowledg it.</p>
                  <p>I found him Ignorant in the Principles of the Chriſtian Faith; therefore I took the more pains to inform him of the danger of dying in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Perſwaſion, which is groſly oppoſite, by the Mixture of many abſurd Traditions, to the ſaving Fundamentals of Chriſtianity. He ſaid, That he did not believe many Points of <hi>Popery; viz.</hi> The Power of <hi>Prieſtly Abſolution,</hi> nor the Merits of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98865:7"/>
                     <hi>Good Works</hi> to claim Salvation by: Nor that it was Lawful to Pray to any <hi>Saint</hi> or <hi>Angel:</hi> And that no <hi>Sin</hi> was <hi>Venial</hi> in its own Nature, though it were never ſo ſmall. I much wondred, that he ſhould ſay, He believed not any of theſe <hi>Popiſh</hi> Points; and yet, that he ſhould wear a <hi>Crucifix</hi> at his Girdle. I deſired him, not to put any Religion in Looking on It, nor in Kiſſing of It. He ſaid, He put no Confidence of Salvation in It; only It was a Remembrance of his Bleſſed <hi>Saviour.</hi> I told him, That <hi>Chriſt</hi> had left no ſuch, nor any other Memorials of Himſelf, but only in the Scriptures of Sacred Truth, and in the Sacraments: That it is the Office of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> to bring every Truth neceſſary for Salvation, to our Remembrance: And that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his Offices and Merits, were only to be Believed in; and were ſufficient to put us in mind of our Duty, and to quicken holy Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in us.</p>
                  <p>I ſaid moreover, That it was a more Refined peice of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> to Conceive otherwiſe of <hi>God</hi> in our Thoughts, than as He had Revealed himſelf by the Scriptures of Truth, in his Infinite Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies. And therefore, to relieve us, in preventing any groſs Miſtakes in our abſurd Imaginations of <hi>God,</hi> we were bound to fix our Thoughts and Conceptions in Prayer, upon <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as Incarnate; who is the only expreſs Image of the <hi>Deity,</hi> and not any Corporeal, diſhonorable Miſ-repreſentations of <hi>God,</hi> by the help of Pictures or Crucifixes.</p>
                  <p>I found alſo, that his <hi>Popiſh</hi> Education had ſtrongly prevailed on him, to adhere to the falſe and abſurd Dotages of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church: For when I told him, That it was not ſafe to Dye in that Religion; He replyed, <hi>That he was reſolved to hold and perſevere in it, becauſe he had been Bred up in it.</hi> I ſaid, That could not be a ſolid Argument; for then he might be as Peremptory to dye in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful State, becauſe the Principles of a Corrupt Nature were rivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his Heart, and were grown familiar to him by Cuſtom.</p>
                  <p>He was ſometimes Pettiſh; yet when the Fit was off, he harkned to my Advice, and joyned with me in Prayer. I deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, not to mock <hi>God,</hi> either by any deliberate Wandring in his Thoughts, while I ſhould pray; nor by ſaying any <hi>Ave-Maryes,</hi> or <hi>Popiſh</hi> Petitions, ſecretly to himſelf. He promiſed me, he would not. He was troubled for his ſinful Courſe of Life: Yet I told him, That was not Repentance deep enough. <hi>David</hi>'s Heart was the Centre of his Remorſe; and that not only his heinous-Crimes of Murder and Adultery, were his Burthen, but the Senſe of his vile Corrupt Nature, which was the poyſonous Spring of all ſcandalous Impieties. And that, as we are in our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98865:8"/>Thankſgivings for Divine Mercies, to Aſcend to the Free-Grace of <hi>God,</hi> in giving <hi>Chriſt</hi> to Redeem us, as the Spring-head of all Spiritual Benefits; So, in a penitent Confeſſion of Sin, we muſt likewiſe Aſcend to the Guilt and Defylement of Original Sin, whence all Actual Abominations flow. That this is a great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief to us, when we cannot make a diſtinct Particular Enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Sins: And that no Hypocrite can be truly humbled for the ſin of his Corrupt Nature, nor for Goſpel-Unbelief, which is the direct damning Sin, as being againſt the very Remedy of our Recovery from a State of Sin and Miſery.</p>
                  <p>Every day, after ſutable Advices given to him, I Pray'd with him. He had not been Grammarred in that ſtrange Diſtinction, which moſt of thoſe <hi>Popiſh</hi> Malefactors had learn't, That a <hi>Papiſt</hi> may lawfully deſire a <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Prayers at Home; yet that his Joyning in Prayer, is an owning of their reputed Hereſie; whoſe Breath is Infectious, when poured out in the Solemnity of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mutually in each others Preſence. <hi>Hill</hi> had learnt this Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, though <hi>Staley</hi> and <hi>Berry,</hi> as well as <hi>Green,</hi> had not. I believe, the true reaſon, why all the other Criminals denyed me Liberty to Pray with them, was, Leſt I ſhould touch too diſtinctly upon the right Sore, (which they palliated, yea denyed) and ſo dreaded that Trouble and Perplexity, which might thereby be raiſed in their Conſciences.</p>
                  <p>I can give no further Account of <hi>Green,</hi> but only this, That upon the Day before his Execution, he told me, That he had received much Information by my Diſcourſes, and Benefit by my Prayers, in order to fit him for his Death: He thank't me for my Viſits, but diſcharged me from farther Attendance upon him; ſo I went not with him to the Place of Execution, to obſerve what End he made.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>VII. Mr. <hi>Hill.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis <hi>Hill</hi> was one of the Murtherers of Sir <hi>Edmundbury God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey.</hi> He was Born and Bred a <hi>Papiſt.</hi> He was not a Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, as was reported; but the Son of a Shoo-maker. He ſaid, That he had been Servant to a <hi>Recuſant Lady,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged ſome of her Concernments; and went over Sea ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, to give her an Account thereof. That he had lately hired an houſe for himſelf to Dwell in; But was not preſent at the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Murther: Yea, that he knew nothing of it, more or leſs, neither before nor after. This he often averred with ſo many ſelf-Imprecations, that I was afraid to urge him for the preſent, to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98865:8"/>any farther Acknowledgment; leſt I might thereby, give him an Occaſion to aggravate his Sin, and ſeal up his Damnation with greater Obduration and Impenitency. I unfolded to him, the wide Difference betwixt the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Religion;</hi> and that the Latter could not be a Religion Inſtituted by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe It was founded in Blood, and propagated by Artifices of Cruelty, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, Violence, Equivocations, and Perjuries: Yea, even by falſe Appeals to the Omniſcient Judge of Innocency, when Crimes were Juridically proved againſt the Appellants.</p>
                  <p>I ſaid, That this was the deepeſt Policy of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> fetcht from the <hi>Conclave</hi> of <hi>Hell:</hi> For, ſuch daring and Atheiſtical Appellants, are not only poſſeſt with the Spirit of Lying, and ſtrongly delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (while Living) to believe a falſe, abſurd Religion; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, do as ſtrangely, out of an obſtinate, impenitent Heart, pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate Bloody Crimes with a flat Denyal of them, after Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof by due Proceſs of Law. Surely, ſuch a Violation of the Sentiments of Conſcience, muſt needs proceed from an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtical Denyal of <hi>God</hi>'s Omniſcient Inſpection, or a Prophane Doubting of the Future Judgment. As if falſe Appellants had not Souls capable of Damnation, or ſtudied how to ſeal it up more firmly to themſelves: But ſuch ſtudied Evaſion of their Crimes, render them blacker and more horrid, while they would make Credulous Perſons ſuſpect their Accuſers to be Perjured; which is a Sin of that deep Dye, and Malignity, that it rarely admits of any Repentance in the Sinner, or Pardon from <hi>God.</hi> Yet ſo hardned are ſome, that they will ſtand out in the Denyal of their Crimes (though proved againſt them) to the laſt Breath. They are not afraid to look the Almighty Judge in the Face, with a Lye in their Mouth.</p>
                  <p>But then, ſuch frontleſs ſtupid Sinners preſume, they ſhall have this Relief as a Shield, to keep off their Damnation; that their Self-Imprecation was for the promoting of a greater Good; <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Romiſh Religion</hi> may not lye under the Reproach of a Blood-thirſty Diſpoſition, in its Profeſſing Party; leſt, being hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in its Propagation, if this were credited, it ſhould gradually become ſo Abominable, as to be rooted out.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Papiſts</hi> think, that they may lawfully, ſafely, yea commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, Perjure themſelves, to promote their falſe Religion; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, if in a Tranſport of Zeal, they Imprecate themſelves, that they may ſit higher in the Good Opinion, and Implicit Faith of their blinded Proſelytes. Such was <hi>Hill!</hi> Who was not more ſubtilly Moulded unto, than deeply Confirmed in all <hi>Popiſh</hi> Principles. Hence it was, that he would not admit of any Information, which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98865:9"/>might beget the leaſt ſuſpicion of their Falſity: Yet this was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Commendable in him, that when I exhorted him to take a ſtrict Review of his Sins; that ſo, being deeply humbled for them, he might obtain ſome hopeful Proſpect of their Pardon: He replyed, <hi>That he had endeavoured to ſearch out whatever might provoke the Lord to deſert him, and ſuffer him to fall under the fatal Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence pronounced upon him.</hi> He ſaid, <hi>He had been Guilty of Sins enough, for which he was thus ſeverely puniſht:</hi> Among the reſt, he inſtanced in this; <hi>That he had wronged one in a Twelve-penny matter; but he was now ſo troubled about it, that he had made Reſtitution ſince his Condemnation; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he was in extream want of Neceſſaries for his preſent Subſiſtence.</hi> I Commended this in him; but withal told him, That there was one Crime committed by him, for which he could never make any Satisfaction; <hi>viz.</hi> The Murthering of Sir <hi>Edmund:</hi> yet, that upon his true Repentance, <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Blood-ſhed was All-ſufficient to waſh away the Stain and Reproach of this moſt Prodigious Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs.</p>
                  <p>He ſtill ſtood out in a peremptory Denyal, <hi>That he knew any thing of it, more or leſs.</hi> And in the uſual Canting Language, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, <hi>That he was as Innocent of it, as the Child unborn.</hi> Which Words may admit of an Equivocation: For the <hi>Child unborn</hi> is <hi>Innocent,</hi> as not being Capable of committing or declaring the Heinouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch a Crime. But though <hi>Hill</hi> was Capacitated for it, with all imaginable Principles of <hi>Jeſuitical Subtilty;</hi> yet his deepeſt Sophiſtry appeared, in pretending to be as <hi>Innocent as the Child un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born; viz.</hi> In this Senſe, <hi>Innocent,</hi> as not able to declare his Guilty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ſaid Murther: For ſo he might be unable, in reſpect of an Oath of Secreſie, which was the Seal of his Impenitency. Or, he might think to Evade the Confeſſion of it, by this Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, <hi>viz.</hi> I am as <hi>Innocent</hi> of the Fact, as there is Truth in this, That the <hi>Child unborn</hi> is here preſent, reſerving this Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Aſſertion unto himſelf. And then it being unriddled in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> it comes to thus much, <hi>I am as Innocent of the Fact laid to my Charge;</hi> that is, There is as much Truth in affirming This, as there is in the <hi>Childs</hi> being preſent, which is yet <hi>Unborn:</hi> For there is not Truth in either.</p>
                  <p>I did fear, that ſome ſuch Equivocation might ſhroud it ſelf under <hi>Hill</hi>'s flat Denyal of the ſaid Murther: Therefore, I told him, That his Ingenuity in Confeſſing a pecuniary Wrong, and making Reſtitution, could not demonſtrate any ſound Repentance, unleſs he took the Shame of this Murther upon himſelf, by a free Confeſſion of it. For a ſincere Penitentiary dares not conceal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſin, though of never ſo Ignominious a Nature. He replyed,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98865:9"/>
                     <hi>That he had taken Shame to himſelf, in confeſſing his doing Wrong, and that he had violated the Integrity, and Peace of his Conſcience, for a very Trifle: Therefore, I could not think, he denyed the Murther laid to his Charge, that he might maintain his Reputation.</hi> But to Confute this Plea: I knew a Fellon, who deny'd the Robbery for which he was Condernned; yet probably to inſinuate into me a good Opinion of him, he Confeſt that he once Robb'd a poor man going to Market, but being afterward troubled in his Conſcience for ſo doing, he inquired out where the perſon wronged Lived, and ſent him double Reſtitution; <hi>becauſe happily</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>the poor man loſing of his market, might have gain'd as much as I ſent him, by ſelling the Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he was carrying thither.</hi> Thus ſome will pretend to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious in Confeſſing hidden Crimes, and yet will ſtand out in denying ſuch which are proved againſt them. This is but a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit remorſe.</p>
                  <p>On the day before <hi>Hills</hi> his Execution, he diſcharged me of farther attendance, becauſe he ſaid, he would be in greater retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to fit himſelf for his Death, now ſo neerly approaching: whereupon I took leave of him; and he prayd God to reward me for all my Viſits of him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>VIII. Mr. <hi>Berry.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BErry</hi> the Porter of <hi>Summerſet-houſe,</hi> was one of the Murtherers of Sir <hi>Edmunbury Godfrey,</hi> and was Executed ſome time after <hi>Hill</hi> and <hi>Green.</hi> He willingly admitted me to Viſit him for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny days, ſomtimes twice in the ſame day. I found him dejected at the firſt, yet afterwards he was reduced to a more compoſed frame. I obſerved that he had ſome books in his Chamber; of all which I took an inſpection, and found no popiſh Author among them. I told him, that I much approved of his Care in the Choice of thoſe Books, eſpecially of the Bible, to be his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates and Guides in his ſolitary Confinement. Then I adviſed him, to ſearch his Heart-ſtate God-ward, and to conſider for what ſpecial ſins God had deſerted him, to fall into ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and notorious a Crime, as the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmundbury God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey;</hi> who had Demonſtrated himſelf to be a worthy Patriot of his Country. He replyed, that he knew nothing of it, neither before, nor after; and that he was no way Acceſſary to the guilt of it. I ſaid, I could not give Credit to him in that; For the Crime was cleerly proved againſt him. I did not much urge him to confeſs it, at that time, fearing I might provoke him to be more ſhie of imbracing any future Viſits or Advice. I bent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98865:10"/>my Diſcourſe, to fit him for his approaching Death; and from Scripture Demonſtrated, that immediatly after the Souls expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, every one is preſented by Angels Good or Evil, (according as their ſtate is, in which they dye) before the dreadful Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of Chriſt, the moſt Impartial righteous Judge of all men. And that of what nature the ſentence which then paſt was of, it was irrepealable: Therefore he could not be too circumſpect in trying his heart-frame, which is naturally deceitful; For if his faith and repentance, (the only qualifications and evidences of a future happy State) were not ſolidly built on Chriſt, as the Rock of Salvation, after his being adjudged, there could not be any retrieval of the Sentence, though it were to the Eternal baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Soul from the bliſs-making Viſion, and fruition of the God of Glory. This awakned him to ſome Remorſe for the ſins of his Life. I then proceeded to adviſe him, not to venture to die in the the Romiſh Perſwaſion; For this could not produce ſolid nor laſting tranquillity in any Conſcience, perplext and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with the guilt of the leaſt ſin. In as much as Papiſts build their hopes of future happineſs on corrupt Principles, <hi>viz.</hi> they mix the belief of the falſities of the Apoſtatical-Trent-Council with the Articles of the Apoſtolical Creed; which can never cement into any conſiſtency of Truth, either in matters of Faith, or Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. I did undertake to diſcover the notorious abſurdity of ſome popiſh Opinions; in doing which, he was not only very atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; but ſaid, he did not believe many things which the Doctors of the Romiſh Church Teach, as neceſſary to be embraced for Articles of the true Faith.</p>
                  <p>I told him, I hoped that he was not ſtubborn in that Hereſy, having declared himſelf better Informed. Yet He did not deny that he was a Papiſt. After much diſcourſe, I drew out a little Treatiſe of one Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw's,</hi> which ſtates in ſhort, but very ſolid Theſes, or Propoſitions, the true nature of Juſtification by Faith in Chriſt; and oppugnes, yea, overthrowes the Popiſh doctrine of Good-works, as Meritorious of Salvation: I Lent it Mr. <hi>Berry,</hi> who having read it, liked it, and ſaid, <hi>He was much ſettled and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the beliefe of that ſound and comfortable Doctrine.</hi> He often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to Pray for, and with him; he was not afraid to be Infected with the breath of an Heretick, as Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the fraternity in Conſpiracy were. I doubt not but whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Counſel, and fervent prayer wrought much on Mr. <hi>Berry,</hi> to bring him to ſome remorſe for his Sinfulneſs; For he gave an eminent ſignal of this in declaring that God had juſtly left <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im to fall under the ſentence of ſo ſhameful a death, for his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98865:10"/>diſſimulation; which was this, <hi>viz.</hi> That he had for his private intereſt, and to ſupply ſome wants he was in, changed his Proteſtant profeſſion, and turned Papiſt, againſt the dictates of his Conſcience, to get into imployment by the favor of that party. This he affirmed more wounded his Conſcience, than all the ſins which he had Committed in the whole Courſe of his Life. Yet ſtill he was very ſhie and reſerved, as unto any acknowledgement of the Notorious Murther of Sir <hi>Edmundberry Godfrey.</hi> But take notice, that a ſincere Conſcience, doth not content it ſelf with the Confeſſion only of ſome particular ſin, but is moſt free and ready to take the ſhame of every ſin, eſpecially of ſuch a crime as wilfull Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, clearly proved againſt him. And that none are ſuch proper Objects of Gods juſt condemnation, as ſuch, who to cover any one ſin, though never ſo ſmall, will ſtudy Evaſions, to deny, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal, or extenuate it.</p>
                  <p>Thus to Cover ſin, is to Add ſin to ſin. The Obligation to puniſhment takes faſter hold, the Guilt remaines uncapable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pardoned: the ſin not confeſt, rankles and feſters in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Haunts the ſinner as an affrighting Ghoſt, yea, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious poyſon ſpreads, till it grow ſo ſtrong in the Malignity of it, that it damns Eternally.</p>
                  <p>This Alarm (or awakening Conſideration) I gave to <hi>Berry,</hi> that I might excite him to an Ingenious Confeſſion of the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmundberry Godfrey;</hi> And beſide, I told him, that there was this danger in not Confeſſing a Crime, that it hardens the heart in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly, to an impudent and impenitent peremptory denyal of it. And that this was the blackeſt mark of a Reprobate. Afterward I prayed with him, that the Lord (who is the ſearcher of all hearts, and the juſt Avenger of all lying and falſe appeals) would incline him to an hearty and free acknowledgement of this very Crime; that he would grant him true and deep Repentance, and ſtrengthen his faith in the Merit of Chriſts Blood, for expiation of ſo great Guilt. <hi>Berry</hi> had a reprieve for ſome time to fit himſelf for death, and I hope he made Good uſe and improvement of it. For when the morning came, wherein he was to be executed, I found him in a more penitent, melting frame than before. I prayed with him at his Execution. I muſt do him this Right, as to ſay, that he was in a very Serious compoſed Temper; For I have ſeldom heard any Malefactor (at the publick place of ſuffering) expreſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in ſuch ſutable and heart-broken petitions, for Divine Pardon, and renewing grace, as <hi>Berry</hi> did: He needed not a prayer-Book in his hand; his Soul-Agonies taught him to pray; Nor did he let
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98865:11"/>fall any thing, which ſmelt in the leaſt of <hi>Popiſh Leaven.</hi> His pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was fervent, and very compoſed, though death ſtared him in the face; yet was he not under any Conſternation or dejection. He ſaid not any thing, either in aſſerting his Innocence as to the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmundberry Godfrey,</hi> neither as to the Religion he dyed in. He fixt his eye upward, and lookt not upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, being very intentive on the great work he was about. I gave him a Large time to prepare and fit himſelf to dye: He made ſome ſecret Ejaculations of his heart Heaven-ward: Then taking a Solemn farewel, I deſired him to reſigne himſelf up to the mercies of God in the alone and All-ſufficient merits of Chriſt, and ſo I went out of the Cart; and after a little time of Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with himſelf, the Sentence of Death was executed upon him.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>AN ACCOUNT OF THE Five Jeſuits, Condemned to be Drawn, Hanged, and Quartered, on <hi>Saturday</hi> the 14th. of <hi>June,</hi> 1679. viz. <hi>Whitebread, Harcourt, Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, Gawen,</hi> and <hi>Turner.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THeſe five Jeſuits having received the aforeſaid Sentence, for Conſpiring the Death of the King, and the ſubvertion of the Proteſtant Religion, I did on the Monday following (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the duty of my Office as Ordinary obliged me) offer to them my aſſiſtance to prepare them for the Execution; but they did not Admit me to their Chambers: Thereupon, I deſiſted from any farther offer to Viſit them. Yet upon the day of their Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution I waited for an opportunity to ſpeak with them before they were, Conducted to the Sledges.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98865:11"/>
                  <head>I. Mr. <hi>Harcourt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>MR. <hi>Harcourt</hi> was firſt brought down from his Chamber, to be carried up to the Chappel, where a dore opens to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh them down the ſtone-ſtairs more conveniently to the Sledges.</p>
                  <p>I thus ſpake to Mr. <hi>Harcourt,</hi> Sir, you did not think fit to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to any Diſourſe in your Chamber, but now that you are upon the very Borders of Death, and muſt be judged to an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal State in Happineſs or Miſery, Conſider well how heinous the Crime is for which you are to ſuffer Death. Beg of God to give you true Repentance unto Life Eternal, and do not ſtand out in the denying or extenuation of your Crime.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Harcourt</hi> made me this ſlight anſwer, <hi>That I needed not to trouble my ſelf concerning Him, for he knew his Duty;</hi> and ſo paſt away from me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>II. Mr. <hi>Whitebread.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THen came Mr. <hi>Whitebread</hi> from his Chamber; I ſaid ſomthing of Adviſe to him as a dying Man, and told him withall, that I had earneſtly pray'd that God would give him Repentance, in order to pardoning Grace and Salvation. This he reſented with more Calmneſs and Modeſty of Spirit than <hi>Harcourt</hi> did, and put off his Hat to me at parting.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III. Mr. <hi>Fenwick.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Had longer Diſcourſe with <hi>Fenwick</hi> in a little Room alone by himſelf. I did Addreſs my ſelf to him in more Pathetick Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, than to the two other, becauſe I had more oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for it. In ſum, I wiſht him to ſearch his heart, becauſe every mans by Nature, is as deceitful as it is Corrupt. That he would pray to God to Undeceive him, as to any falſe hopes of Heaven, and not build on any Sandy Foundation, by truſting to any Humiliation for Sin, or the Merits of any Saint or Angel; And that he would not ſtand out in denying of his Crime. That he would conſider ſeriouſly of that Sacred Scripture in the Twenty eighth of the <hi>Prov.</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Thirteenth <hi>verſe,</hi> He who hides his ſin ſhall not proſper in the attempting of it, but rather expoſes himſelf to a Curſe. But whoſoever Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and forſakes his Sin, ſhall obtain Mercy. He ſaid, <hi>That he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98865:12"/>had Confeſt 'twixt God and himſelf, and that was Sufficient.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I told him, that in reſpect of the great Scandal he had given, and Reproach he had brought upon Religion, which Obliges to all Fidelity towards Princes, and forbids the Subvertion of a Lawful Government, he ought to expreſs great Sorrow for, and deteſtation of ſuch Principles which deſtroy Humane Society.</p>
                  <p>But he angerly replyed, <hi>What! do you undertake to inſtruct me, or others of my Order, as if we were not Men of Reaſon and Learning.</hi> I told him, that I was bound to aſſiſt him as a dying Man; and to put him in mind of ſeeking his Souls Salvation, in a Right way. And that, whereas he ſlighted my Advice, he ought not to look upon any <hi>Proteſtant Divine,</hi> to be like Their Novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whom they Traine up in Ignorance, as if it were the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Devotion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſaid, that I ſtood Amazed, that any man of his Learning ſhould ſo far forfeit the Repute thereof, and all the Sentiments of a Good Conſcience, as to adhere to principles ſo deſtructive to all Order, Equity, and Government eſtabliſht by Light of Nature, even among Savages.</p>
                  <p>He was not pleaſed with my diſcourſe, yet I did aſſure him, I would not deſiſt praying for him, while I could Rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think, that he was Alive, and within the reach or benefit of my prayers. And ſo we parted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>IV, V. Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> and Mr. <hi>Turner.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Could not ſpeak with <hi>Gawen</hi> or <hi>Turner</hi> till they were placed in the Sledge. I ſpake but little to them, Time, and the Noiſe of the people thronging me, would not permit me to ſay much. Only I told Mr. <hi>Gawen,</hi> that Now death ſtared him in the face, and his judgement to an Eternal State was very Near; therefore I adviſed him not to palliate or extenuate his great Crime, much leſſe to deny it; for, he would hazard his Salvation, if he went out of the world with a falſity in his mouth.</p>
                  <p>I told him I had and would continue to pray for him and his Fellow-Criminal in the Sledge with him. So wiſhing them a penitential frame of Heart, that they might obtain Eternal Life in Chriſt, upon the drawing away of the Sledg, Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> ſhewed a publick Signal of Civility to me, and thankt me. He ſeemed much more cheerful than the reſt. And I hope he had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grounds for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98865:12"/>
                  <head>Mr. <hi>Langhorne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AFter Sentence of Death paſt upon the ſaid Unhappy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as being Involved in the <hi>Jeſuitical Conſpiracy</hi> againſt the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Nation;</hi> I Addreſſed my ſelf in a Viſit to him, which he Accepted. When I firſt came into his Chamber, I told him, That I came not to upbraid a Dying Man, though of a contrary <hi>Religion:</hi> That I pittyed him, as a Condemned Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; yet was more troubled, that he ſhould Eſpouſe the <hi>Popiſh Perſwaſions</hi> ſo far, as to Suſpend, or Renounce rather, the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Right Reaſon, in Embracing and Adhering to ſo Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and Abſurd Opinions. He anſwered me, <hi>That he thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a ſurer Way for to attain Salvation, than any of my Opinion could ſet themſelves in. For</hi> Proteſtants (ſaid he) <hi>follow the Miſtakes of their private Judgments; and then cry them up, for the Genuine Interpretation of the Holy Scriptures. But</hi> We (ſaid he) <hi>who are</hi> Roman Catholicks, <hi>have the Conduct of an Infallible Guide, to Interpret obſcure Ambiguities in the Scriptures: For no Scripture is of any</hi> private <hi>Interpretation; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, well-meaning Perſons may propoſe, and put off their Fancies, for ſolid Concluſions, drawn from the ſacred Records of</hi> God's <hi>Word.</hi> He ſaid, <hi>That therefore, there was great need of an external, ſupreme, infallible Judge on Earth; whoſe Deciſion upon Appeals, can only ſtate and determine all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies about matters of Faith and Practice.</hi> I replyed, That the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority of <hi>God,</hi> as impreſt upon the Veracity of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, was never ſeparated from the ſame Spirit, who did Dictate them, <hi>as unto ſpecial Guydance;</hi> ſo far, as not to Deſert ſincere <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that they ſhould fall into any Damnable <hi>Hereſie.</hi> But I feared, that the <hi>Romiſh Opinions</hi> were ſuch, though they be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be Believed and Obeyed, upon the ſcore of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility,</hi> equally with the ſacred <hi>Scriptures.</hi> What Blaſphemy is this, for a ſinful Man to arrogate the Title of <hi>Infallible,</hi> due only to <hi>God,</hi> the Fountain and Architype of all Truth! That the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Lights,</hi> gave Mankind the Beſt and Safeſt Conduct of his own Holy, Infallible <hi>Spirit,</hi> in Matters aforeſaid. And that the Scriptures, being exemplified from his Eſſential Purity and Vera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, were not defective as Human Laws; which require, an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Judge and Interpreter, diſtinct from themſelves, in their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Conſtitution. So that, <hi>in all Things neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> the Scriptures were a Perfect <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Standard,</hi> to dictate and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Matters of Faith, and Chriſtian Obedience. Yet ſo arrogant is the <hi>Pope,</hi> as to Challenge an Authority to Himſelf, to give the Scriptures a Sanction; yea, to Over-rule them by his Corrupt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98865:13"/>Traditions, which he declares <hi>Infallible.</hi> Thus he Exautorats, and Invalidates their Divine Original, and Superintendency; as if they received all the Life of their Interpretation, from his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative Dilucidation, as the <hi>Moon</hi> doth her Light from the <hi>Sun.</hi> Hence it is, that when the <hi>Pope</hi> enters into any Council, he hath the <hi>Bible</hi> placed under his Feet, while ſingly himſelf Over-rules the Council; and Exalts his ſole Determination, above the ſacred Records of Truth. Hence it is, that under a Pretence, that the Scriptures are Obſcure, and a dead Letter in themſelves, that they muſt be Animated with his Traditions, though never ſo Abſurd and Contradictory to their Divine Authority, Certainty, and Perfection.</p>
                  <p>Alſo I ſaid, That where the Scriptures were Obſcure in one Place, they explained that Ambiguity in another: So that, there was no need of any External Judge. And that <hi>Proteſtant Divines,</hi> did not give <hi>out</hi> their Private Sentiments, and Interpretations of the Scriptures, for Laws, to ſuperſede the Innate Authority of the Scriptures; or to oblige <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to an Implicit Faith and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as the <hi>Pope</hi> doth; who over-rules the very <hi>Scriptures</hi> Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: So that, no part of them is Canonical, but only thoſe Books, which he declares to be ſuch. Thus a ſinful Man judges that ſacred Law, by which himſelf, and all Men muſt be Judged; though he claim a Power to Pardon <hi>Sin,</hi> and Diſpoſe of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Rewards of <hi>Virtue,</hi> or <hi>Vice;</hi> accordingly as himſelf pleaſes to determine the Nature and Circumſtances of Both. Hence I ſaid, It proceeded, that the Opinions of the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> were ſo Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, as moulded and adapted, to ſerve and promote the Carnal Intereſt of his Ambition, and the Licentiouſneſs of his Followers.</p>
                  <p>Then he askt me, <hi>Whether I did not think, that the</hi> Popiſh <hi>and</hi> Proteſtant Religion, <hi>might not be Reducible into a Coalition or Unity?</hi> I anſwered, No; becauſe they were ſo Contrariant, that they could never Cement, ſo as to yield a ſafe Conduct to Eternal Life. Inaſmuch, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf averred, That in vain do all ſuch Worſhip him, who Teach for Divine Doctrines, the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Men: That whoſoever Adds or Diminiſhes from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural-Fundamentals, deſpiſes, and ſeeks to nullify the Wiſdom and Authority of <hi>God</hi> Himſelf. That <hi>Popiſh Principles</hi> undermine, and ſubvert the All-ſufficiency of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the Execution of his Offices. That as <hi>Socinians</hi> cannot be accounted <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the <hi>Divinity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Perſon:</hi> So <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> who Invalidate his <hi>Offices,</hi> are <hi>Anti-Chriſtian,</hi> in their Spirits, and in their Miſ-belief.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, there is no more hope, that two Religions ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, ſhould ever Cement in One, according to the Analogy of <hi>Faith,</hi> preſcribed by <hi>Chriſt;</hi> than that Light and Darkneſs ſhould agree, or have Fellowſhip.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98865:13"/>
                  <p>Nor can there be any Colour of right Reaſon, for that Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; That <hi>Popiſh Traditions</hi> are rather <hi>beſide</hi> the Rule and Dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> than directly <hi>contrary</hi> to them. For, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is not agreeable to the Revealed, Perfect Will of <hi>God,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly, or by natural Conſequence, or by right Deduction, it is a Sin. Conſider, There is as little Hope and Comfort for that Perſon, who falls into a River, by ſlipping betwixt, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Bridge; as for him, who directly caſts himſelf into It. Both may be Drowned irrecoverably. The One, out of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advertency, or Miſtake of a Drunken Giddyneſs: The Other, out of the Preſumption of a ſullen Obſtinacy. There are more Ways which lead to Death, than the direct Stabbing of one's ſelf. So, Tranſgreſſion on the Right-Hand, in a Superſtitious Zeal, may ruin a Man's Soul, as certainly, as down-right <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After theſe Diſcourſes, I askt Mr. <hi>Langhorne,</hi> That I might Pray with him? He anſwered me, <hi>No; Yet, I deſire your Prayers at Home.</hi> He ſaid, <hi>That Prayer in Preſence, was an Act of Communion; but it was unfit, to joyn with One, who was not a Member of the</hi> Roman Church. I replyed, That I thought, there was little or no Difference in ſuch diſtinct Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; however, it could not be any unlawful Act. He would not Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me to Pray <hi>with</hi> him: Therefore, to root out ſuch a Scruple, I ſhall ſtate now, more at large, what I then ſpake more ſuccinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Is not Prayer an Univerſal Duty, and a Teſtification of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charity? Therefore, to limit It only to ſuch, who are Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into any Faction, is to look on all others, as Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Hope of Salvation by him, as the only Head; who Influences the Univerſal Church, with the Spirit of Faith, Unity, and Concord.</p>
                  <p>Can any <hi>Papiſt</hi> think to receive Benefit by Prayer, himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſent; who hath not ſo much Charity, as to bear <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Preſence, in Praying together? What proud Singularity is this? What Inconveniency can happen, from a <hi>Proteſtants</hi> joyning with a <hi>Papiſt</hi> in Prayer, if they do not mix their Private Opinions (which are fitter for a Diſputation) in the time of Praying together? Such Imprudence would turn Prayer, which is the Badge of <hi>Chriſtian Communion,</hi> into an occaſion of Reproach; and imbitter each others Spirits, to remain at a farther diſtance. To prevent ſuch a Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, let them conſent, that they will keep cloſe to Scripture. Matter, and Phraſes in Prayer; becauſe in theſe, they are agreed. So ſhall they not grieve each other, by an uncharitable Exagita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and venting of their private Opinions. Yet I deny not, but that they ought to deſire of <hi>God,</hi> that he would clear up to them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98865:14"/>his Truth and Ways more fully; and that, in whatever they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, by way of Miſtake about Opinions Forreign, to the Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Parts, and Fundamentals of <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> they may come to a right Underſtanding of each other; and may recede from any falſe Mixtures, ſuper-added to <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s pure Religion. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to deny any <hi>Proteſtant Divine,</hi> to Pray with <hi>Popiſh Perſons</hi> Coni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, when they cannot have the Relief thereof, from any of their own Perſwaſion; leſt they ſhould Confirm them in their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Principles, or joyn wicked Counſels, to diffuſe their Treaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Deſigns, by Meſſages, to put Plots in Execution, is a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to deny them the Aſſiſtance of their own Party. Yet they ſtick not, to grow ſullen and inſolent, in rejecting the Prayers of <hi>Proteſtant Divines.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How careleſs of, and cruel to their own Souls, are ſuch, who will not by all Lawful Helps, ſecure and promote their Souls ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Bleſſedneſs! Is not this ſuch a Breach of Charity, as to make voyd their own Prayers for Themſelves? and to limit <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion,</hi> only to the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> which is but a Corner of the <hi>Chriſtian World;</hi> and cannot be properly <hi>Catholick,</hi> unleſs It embrace an <hi>Univerſal Charity</hi> for <hi>All Chriſtians,</hi> who Profeſs the ſame <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the ſame Fundamentals of <hi>Chriſtianity?</hi> But <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> have not ſo departed from the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> as to hate all Perſons of her <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety;</hi> but only, their Corruptions in Doctrine and Practice. We deny not to them, the <hi>Duties</hi> of <hi>Common Charity;</hi> or ſuch <hi>Requiſite Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtances</hi> at the time of <hi>Extreme Sickneſs,</hi> or <hi>Death,</hi> which may ſafely conſiſt with their not being Confirmed in <hi>Popiſh Principles,</hi> too deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rooted in them already; and the <hi>Conſiſtency</hi> of the <hi>Eſtabliſht Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh Church,</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> After theſe Conferences with Mr. <hi>Langhorne,</hi> I askt him, Whether he were the very Perſon Accuſed before the <hi>Committee</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> in 1666; for being Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious, at leaſt, of the <hi>Conflagration</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>Treachery:</hi> Becauſe Mr. <hi>Richard Langhorne,</hi> Counſellor at the <hi>Temple,</hi> is ſaid in a Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon Oath, to have caſt out Threatning Words about the ſaid <hi>Conſpiracy?</hi> — He anſwered me, <hi>That he was the Perſon then Accuſed; but knew no more of the Firing of</hi> London, <hi>than he did of this</hi> Plot. But what he knew of This, is ſufficiently Demonſtrated, by his being Condemned, and Executed for a Well-wiſher to It, and Agent in It. I offer'd a ſecond Viſit to him, on the <hi>Thurſday</hi> before his <hi>Execution;</hi> but he ſent me Thanks, and deſired to be wholly Retired to himſelf. So being in the <hi>Country</hi> when he was Executed, I cannot give any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there Account concerning him.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98865:14"/>
            <head>THE Falſe Appealing <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> Silenced and Confuted: OR, <hi>A Diſcovery of their Falſe Courage and Chearfulneſs at Execution; how differenced from the hidden</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>of Real</hi> Martyrs.</head>
            <p>I Do more than probably believe, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> appenls relating to their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, were meer Equivocations; and that I may not be cenſured to wrong them by a ſuſpicion only, I ſhall Endeavour to prove, that they made falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies and Appeals. This I ſhall do three ways.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> I will preſent you, with many Aſſertions of the Doctors of their own Church and Society, who maintain Equivocation, yea down right Perjury, Lawful in thoſe Circumſtances, which occurred to theſe <hi>Jeſuits.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall demonſtrate, how Sutably they drew the Coppy of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, after the Original Pattern ſet them by the Precedent Fathers of the ſame Society.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I ſhall Demonſtrate, how deep-dyed a Sin it is, how great miſchief it doth, and what exemplary remarkable puniſhment, God uſually inflicts on ſuch falſe Appellants.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> IT is very likely, theſe <hi>Jeſuits</hi> were Induced to make Equivocating Appeals when dying, becauſe ſo many Doctors of their Church aſſert theſe to be Venial, nay Lawful in many Caſes. <hi>Soto,</hi> who was a Principal Divine in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> He acknowledges Perjury to be a greater Sin than Murther: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he maintains the Violation of <hi>Promiſſory and Aſſertory Oaths,</hi> to be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Venial, not Mortal Sins, how habitual and enſtomary ſoever they be:</hi> So that, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, the dint of the Magiſtrates juſt Sentence, may be <hi>avoided,</hi> or the <hi>Catholick Cauſe</hi> promoted.</p>
            <p>Now, if <hi>raſh</hi> Appeals be (in the <hi>right</hi> Conſtruction of them) a great Contempt of God, <hi>Falſe Ones</hi> muſt needs be an high degree of <hi>Blaſphemy and Atheiſm.</hi> Theſe, joyned with ſelf-Imprecations, are a <hi>Mocking</hi> of the Divine Majeſty, and the ſending up of a <hi>Challenge</hi> to the God of Truth, to damn the Appellant, if he ſpeaks what is Falſe, or any way Conceals the Truth. Yet in the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> account, not only Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious Lyes, but <hi>downright Perjuries are Lawful;</hi> when they may ſerve the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of their Church, <hi>maintain</hi> their falſe Doctrine, or <hi>Conceal</hi> their Helliſh Deſignes. It is a great poice of <hi>Piety,</hi> to make Lies for the promoting of their Religion; So <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davious Vives,</hi> and <hi>Eſpencaeus Comment in Tim.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 11. pag. 156.</p>
            <p>Here it is to be Obſerv'd, that the third <hi>Lateran Council</hi> decreed it Lawful, to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and Kill any Prince Infected with Hereſy <hi>(that is to ſay)</hi> being a Profeſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. Hereupon, theſe <hi>Jeſuits</hi> thought, <hi>They needed not the help of an Equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> in aſſerting of their Innocency; becauſe by the <hi>Maxims</hi> of their Bloody and Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Divinity, they affirm that it is <hi>better,</hi> to ſuffer a King to be Slain, than <hi>to reveal</hi> the Conſeſſion, of ſuch a deſign intended. So <hi>Eudaemon in Apolog. Garneti.</hi> ch. 13. And <hi>Suarez Tractatu de Panitentia,</hi> That the Lord gave to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and Conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>Pope,</hi> Power to make <hi>that which is ſin, to be no Sin</hi> So <hi>Bellarm, in Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laium.</hi> ch. 31. That to Kill a King who is depoſed, is not to Kill <hi>a King,</hi> but only a <hi>private</hi> Perſon. So <hi>Tolet, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>De Inſtructione Sacerdotali.</hi> ch 58.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98865:15"/>
            <p>That, he is not a Murtherer, who Kills an Excommunicated Perſon, being <hi>poſſeſt with Zeal towards our Mother, the Catholick Church.</hi> — So, <hi>Pope <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban,</hi> in the 23d. <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and 5th. <hi>Queſtions</hi> That the Sentences, Decrees, and Judgments of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, who are Excommunicated, (<hi>as all</hi> Proteſtants <hi>are by them</hi>) are <hi>Voyd, and of no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> So <hi>Tolet, lib. primo, De Inſtutione Sacerdotali.</hi> cap. 13. That the <hi>Pope</hi> is Lord of all the <hi>Temporal Poſſeſſions</hi> of Kingdoms. — So <hi>Bellarm.</hi> in <hi>Barklaium.</hi> cap. 21.</p>
            <p>Cardinal <hi>Du Perron,</hi> in his <hi>Oration</hi> made to the States in <hi>Paris,</hi> (upon the 15th. of <hi>January,</hi> 1615.) doth not think it fit, that a <hi>King</hi> ſhould be Killed, but only Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; <hi>which is all one, as to Condemn him to Dye:</hi> Becauſe <hi>(as they ſay)</hi> from the time of his Depoſing, he is no more a <hi>Lawful King;</hi> but an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper.</hi> Now, every <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> of a Kingdom, may Lawfully be Killed. The ſaid Cardinal, <hi>Equivocates</hi> in his Advice. For, he ſpeaks to this <hi>Effect:</hi> Let us not Kill an <hi>Heretical King,</hi> but De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him. <hi>That is; Let us however, Diſarme him of his Authority, that he may be Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</hi> Let us take his <hi>Title</hi> from him, which is a <hi>Means to preſerve</hi> his Life. Let us <hi>not</hi> Kill him, <hi>while</hi> he is a <hi>King;</hi> but let us Depoſe him: And <hi>then,</hi> who ever Kills him, ſhall not Kill a <hi>King.</hi> Theſe Sayings, are full of <hi>Contradiction, and very Weakly, yea Wickedly, ſet together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By ſuch <hi>Popiſh Principles,</hi> the very <hi>Foundations</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Government,</hi> are quite blown up; as if they had been <hi>at the Mercy of</hi> Faux. They hold, That the Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Heretical,</hi> (becauſe It will not ſtoop to the Yoke of <hi>Anti-Chriſtian Tyranny</hi>) hath no Government properly Its Own; No <hi>King,</hi> no Subjects, no Parliament, no Laws, Liberties, or Propriety in any thing. They think, they may deal with Us, as <hi>Monſters</hi> of Mankind, who have forſeited all into their Hands; and nothing ſhall hinder them from taking Poſſeſſion, any longer, than till they can Maſter the Power of our Severeign Lord, the <hi>King,</hi> and his Laws.</p>
            <p>They deny, we can have any <hi>Legal Parliament;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Peers,</hi> (they alleadge) are <hi>Infamous as Hereticks.</hi> And Free-holders, to Chooſe and be Choſen for Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>have no Propriety.</hi> None have Power <hi>(they ſay)</hi> by Conſequence, to Make <hi>Laws,</hi> to Require or Grant <hi>Subſidies:</hi> For no Order of Men, among Hereticks, <hi>have any thing of their Own, to Give or Grant.</hi> All is Forfeited from them, for their <hi>Hereſie.</hi> They hold, That our Laws are of no more Force, than the <hi>Agreement of a Company of Robbers:</hi> Becauſe, being Excommunicated, we are, <hi>Ipſo Facto,</hi> Diveſted of all Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Right, and Propriety in our Laws, Eſtates, Liberties, and Municipal Priviledges. So that, theſe <hi>Jeſuits</hi> pleaded Innocency, becauſe they Acted <hi>By and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the</hi> Pope's <hi>Commiſſion;</hi> which is Preſumptively-Conſtructive, for Depraedation of our Goods, and the Deſtruction of our Lives, upon his Iſſuing out the Sentence of <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; though no Declaration ſhould expreſly injoyn the Execution of</hi> Rapine <hi>and</hi> Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>To be ſure, He who will Regulate himſelf by <hi>Their Maxims,</hi> may Act any Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs in the World, without any fear of <hi>Deadly Guilt.</hi> Yet, <hi>That Church</hi> pretends to a <hi>Monopoly of All the Holineſs upon Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They may <hi>perſiſt till Death,</hi> in all Perfidiouſneſs to <hi>God</hi> and Man, in Breach of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Compacts, in all Lying and Perjuries, in Slandering or Detraction; yea, in all Unmercifulneſs and Cruelty to <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> and yet, <hi>Not fall ſhort of Salvation,</hi> if theſe <hi>Impoſtors</hi> may be truſted upon their <hi>Own Maxims.</hi> Theſe abominable Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>are but Specks or Motes;</hi> not <hi>Againſt</hi> the Law of <hi>God,</hi> (the End of which, is <hi>Charity</hi>) but only <hi>Beſide</hi> It. So <hi>Durandus, Vega, Rada, Herrera, Eſtius, Becanus.</hi> All theſe afore-mentioned Crimes, are but <hi>Peccadilioes</hi> in Their account, when Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> For, they owe <hi>Theſe, No Charity;</hi> and therefore, may juſtly Contrive their Deſtruction, as <hi>Hereticks.</hi> If an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> had a mind, to render the Chriſtian Name <hi>Odious,</hi> and the Goſpel a <hi>Licentious Doctrine,</hi> tending to <hi>Debauch</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; He could need no greater Argument, but only <hi>This, viz.</hi> To perſwade Men, that the <hi>Maxims</hi> of the <hi>Roman Divines,</hi> are <hi>Conformed to the Rules of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and</hi> Chriſtianity. For, Do not <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctors <hi>Reverence</hi> Hypocriſie, as an <hi>Holy Art?</hi> A Lye, though very <hi>Groſs,</hi> is only <hi>Venial</hi> in <hi>Their</hi> account, unleſs it do <hi>Much</hi> Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief; <hi>not ſo,</hi> when it is only againſt <hi>Truth it ſelf.</hi> Thus, it may be <hi>as Innocent,</hi> to tell Lies, <hi>as Truth; and as Criminal to ſpeak Truth, as Lies.</hi> There will be no Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in their <hi>Own Nature,</hi> unleſs by accident, they do Hurt <hi>Alike.</hi> Thus <hi>Soto, ibid. Lib</hi> 5. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 7. <hi>Artic.</hi> 4. Pag. 168. Yea, <hi>Antonius Corduba</hi> determins, that a Perſon Interrogated by a Judge, whether ſuch a Crime were Committed by him, may <hi>ſtifly Deny It,</hi> (although he <hi>Did It</hi>) with this <hi>Reſerva, I am not bound to Diſcover It;</hi> though
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98865:15"/>he be upon his Oath, to declare the whole Truth. He may Equivocate in uſual Form, ſayes <hi>Lopez. cap.</hi> 51. <hi>pag.</hi> 264. <hi>Angel Sum. V. Confeſſ. N.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Yea, <hi>Popiſh Doctors</hi> have Devices to <hi>Legitimate</hi> the worſt Wickedneſs. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſayes, If the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould forbid Vertue, and command Vice, the <hi>Church</hi> muſt <hi>practice Vioe,</hi> or <hi>ſin againſt Her Conſcience.</hi> If the <hi>Pope</hi> can diſpenſe with Vows, which are <hi>Solemn Promiſes made to God,</hi> why not with the Guilt of <hi>Falſe Appeals?</hi> So <hi>Canus, pars Sexta, Relict de Paenitentia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some affirm, That the <hi>Pope</hi> can <hi>Legitimate</hi> Inceſt: If ſo, by the ſame Reaſon he may pardon Falſe Appeals. For, What are ſuch, but a Spiritual Inceſt, committed 'twixt the Heart and Tongue; which ought to agree in ſpeaking Truth, for this is the Souls-Chaſtity? They count it better than Innocent, to abuſe the VVorld with Lies, even in point of Religion. Surely, if the Injury be not Great there, wherein can it be Small? Yea, they allow of Lies, in their very Devotion. <hi>Peter Abbot</hi> of <hi>Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> declares That in one <hi>Church-Hymne,</hi> in the Praiſe of St. <hi>Bennet,</hi> he found Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-four Lyes, at leaſt. They affirm, That they may ſafely Lye, in Confeſſing, that they abhor the Sin confeſt: Yet themſelves look upon the <hi>Confeſſors Chair,</hi> as the <hi>Divine Tribunal.</hi> So <hi>Angelus, Sylveſter, Navar.</hi> Cap. 21. Num. 37. <hi>Covarruvius, Soto, Bannes.</hi> Now, if they may lawfully Lye, in doing Penance; when or wherein will they ſpeak Truth? If ſuch a Sacred Part of their Religion be thus Prophaned, we may well conclude, that whereſoever they find any Liberty for ſpeech, they muſt have Licenſe to Lye, and that <hi>ex Officio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor can we rationally expect from <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> that they will Swear the Truth at <hi>Death.</hi> You will ſay, Then <hi>Conſcience</hi> is more awakned, made quick and ſerious in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rective and Corrective Part of its Office. So that, the moſt profligate ſort of Sinners, when Dying, will not dare but to declare the Truth. I reply: Yet <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Deſigners upon <hi>Mens Conſciences,</hi> to ſeat themſelves as Over-awing <hi>Demi-Gods</hi> therein, while they dictate Cheats and Dotages unto them.</p>
            <p>Yea, How do theſe <hi>Seducers</hi> Inſtruct their Novices, to believe ſuch ſtrange Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, which Themſelves deny at <hi>Death?</hi> Then they deteſt all <hi>Lying Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Miracles;</hi> as alſo, all <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> for <hi>Equivocating.</hi> This they pretend to do, when they have a Proſpect of <hi>Damnation</hi> at <hi>Death;</hi> and to make the World believe, that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Charge them with Falſe Imputations. Yet I cannot ſuppoſe them to be <hi>Serious,</hi> in Renouncing their Falſe Tenets at Death. For, if they did heartily do it, How could they averr, that they Dyed in the Profeſſion of the <hi>Romiſh Church?</hi> What Contradictions are theſe <hi>Aſſeverations?</hi> If they ſpake the Truth, <hi>when Dying,</hi> then were they <hi>Apoſtats</hi> from that <hi>Religion,</hi> which themſelves ſtyle <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick.</hi> Theſe <hi>Jeſuitical Impoſtors</hi> dread not Damnation it ſelf, while they turn themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Forms; and for their Intereſt, affirm and deny the ſame thing in a Breath; whereas Truth is the ſame Eternally, and Alters not. Yet, theſe Men live by a falſe Religion, for Earthly Intereſt and Grandeur: But, after all their Diſſimulation and Intrigues, ſeem to Dye in the right Religion, Inſtituted by <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it was, That they <hi>Diſclaimed</hi> the Merit of <hi>Good Works;</hi> and at their Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, did not ſo much as <hi>Touch upon any Thing groſly different,</hi> from the Purity of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> Hence it was, that they Pray'd not <hi>Audibly</hi> to any Saint or Angel: For, had they <hi>Groſly Contradicted</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> at their Death, their Appeals (they thought) would not ſo <hi>Cleverly</hi> have been Believed by Credulous, Vulgar Minds. <hi>It may be,</hi> in their Appeal to <hi>God,</hi> they Equivocated, and <hi>meant,</hi> that they Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to the <hi>Pope;</hi> whom they ſtyle, <hi>Their Lord God,</hi> as ſeated High in the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their Hearts. For they give little leſs, than <hi>Divine Honour</hi> to Him, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming, that his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nholyneſs-Abſolution,</hi> is an <hi>Immediate Ticket,</hi> to Challenge <hi>Heaven</hi> by, and to waſh them clean from the <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Reproach</hi> of the Greateſt Villanies.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs, theſe Appealers were ſo well <hi>known to,</hi> and Approved by his Holineſs, as it was a Wonder, that he did not <hi>work a Miracle</hi> for their Impunity. However, It is likely, that he <hi>ſo far</hi> honored theſe Eldeſt Sons in the Myſtery of Iniquity, that they eſcapt <hi>Purgatory</hi> by ſome rare Contrivance, and were Dignifyed Saints imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after Death, <hi>for being Knights of the Poſt.</hi> Doubtleſs they were <hi>hardned in</hi> this preſumption, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath power to <hi>Diſpence with</hi> the Sentiments of right reaſon, yea can make void the <hi>poſitive Duties of the Divine Law.</hi> Hence it is the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Doctrine of their Church,</hi> That it is not Lawful <hi>to keep Faith</hi> with <hi>Hereticks,</hi> in promiſſory Oaths, or <hi>Aſſertory Juſtifications</hi> of their Integrity. <hi>Romiſh</hi> Doctors affirm, that if the <hi>Pope</hi> conſtitute and declare Virtue to be <hi>Vice,</hi> and the moſt abominable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98865:16"/>Crimes to be <hi>Innocency,</hi> they are bound under the Penalty of Damnation to believe him.</p>
            <p>Now this is to Arrogate a Power <hi>above God himſelf,</hi> who cannot alter the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Nature of Moral Principles, which are ſuch <hi>Fixed Truths,</hi> that what is Right and Juſt, or Wicked and Unjuſt in the Nature of the <hi>thing it ſelf,</hi> was ſuch, <hi>before any</hi> declaration of the Will of God concerning it was ſuperadded. Therefore to <hi>change the Meaſures of Good and Evil,</hi> which are Originally founded in the Eſſential In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecal Goodneſs and Badneſs of <hi>Principles,</hi> is to give a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> to Sin. It is to <hi>Exautorate or Invalidate</hi> the Eternal Principles of Virtue, although theſe be Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht on the very <hi>Dictates of right Reaſon.</hi> This is to <hi>Superſede</hi> and make <hi>void</hi> the Authority of God himſelf, who hath Implanted thoſe <hi>common ſentiments</hi> of what is right or wrong, in the Hearts of all Men. They, who draw all Appeals to the <hi>Pope</hi> for the Deciſion of what we are to believe or practiſe, though contrary to <hi>Divine</hi> Revelation (which is to make God himſelf a Lyar) how can ſuch Miſcreans be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited in the moſt ſolemn Aſſeverations of their Integrity? Had theſe Impoſters turned their Eye, with an <hi>Holy, Awful Reverence upon God,</hi> the <hi>Prototype of Truth;</hi> had they had any regard of his <hi>Omniſcient Inquiſition,</hi> after falſe Appellants, they durſt not have <hi>Challenged</hi> his Juſtice, to detect and puniſh their Impudent Aſſertions. Surely, they <hi>dreamt</hi> of being weighed in Saint <hi>Michaels</hi> Ballance, which is a <hi>Popiſh</hi> inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to deceive dying perſons; as if their <hi>Meritorious</hi> Treaſons for promoting the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Religion, ſhould <hi>Out-weigh</hi> their Lying Appeals; that ſo, they might <hi>not bind a Curſe</hi> upon their Souls, but directly go to Heaven Thus, they did not weigh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the <hi>Even</hi> Ballance of Gods Sacred Law, but flattered themſelves in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances of a deceitful Heart; becauſe any one grain of Sin, makes all real Good works of <hi>no value at all in Gods account,</hi> when he makes a Righteous diſquiſition of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>of our Actions. All the Wayes of a Man, are Clean in his own Eyes; but the Lord weighs the Spirit,</hi> Prov. 16.2. The Heart of a Sinner, often miſtakes the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of its own Actions; and yet, a Falſe <hi>Appeal concerning them, doth not Appale him.</hi> I deſire all Falſe Appellants, to conſider well, how they <hi>Seal up their Damnation to themſelves.</hi> I remember, how the <hi>Wife</hi> ſuſpected of Adultery, was <hi>Tryed</hi> by <hi>God</hi>'s own Order and Appointment, in the 5th. Chapter of <hi>Numb.</hi> The Oblation to Try and Diſcover, was called <hi>An Offering of Memorial, to bring Iniquity to Remembrance,</hi> verſ. the 15th. The Lord's Jealouſie, will wax <hi>Hot,</hi> and his Fury <hi>Flame forth</hi> againſt Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical Appellants. <hi>God</hi> Himſelf, will become a <hi>more Zealous Witneſs,</hi> and as <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere a Judge,</hi> to Entayl their Self-Imprecations upon themſelves, and their Poſterity. The <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s bitter Death and Paſſion, ſhall not <hi>Purge away</hi> their Guilt, nor <hi>Comfort them</hi> in aſſerting of their Innocency: It ſhall rather <hi>Revive</hi> and <hi>ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven their Iniquity, in the horrid Reflexions of their Conſcience.</hi> Their Appeal, ſhall not prove their <hi>Compurgation;</hi> but ſhall more <hi>ſuddenly and ſtrangely Reveal</hi> their Iniquity, to their ſhame: while Upright Souls are made more Fruitful in a Conception of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Thoughts,</hi> and are impregnated with all the Graces of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Spirit.</hi> An Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites Belly ſhall ſwell with <hi>Pain,</hi> while he prepares <hi>Deceit;</hi> and when he falls in Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel with Iniquity, <hi>Satan, (that Lying Spirit)</hi> ſhall take the <hi>Deeper Poſſeſſion</hi> of him. His <hi>Sin ſhall be brought more ſadly to</hi> Remembrance, <hi>Haunt him in the Guilt, and Hunt him to ſwift Deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus a Falſe Appeal, like the <hi>Jealouſie-Water,</hi> ſhall haſten a Conſumption upon the <hi>Credit</hi> of every <hi>Impoſtor.</hi> The Curſe ſhall enter as <hi>Oyl into his Bones;</hi> yea, ſoak <hi>deeper</hi> into his very Soul. Thus <hi>Perjury</hi> binds <hi>firm,</hi> every Self-Imprecation upon the <hi>Hypocritical Appellant.</hi> Such <hi>Proſtituting</hi> of Sinners Conſciences to Perjury, in making falſe <hi>Apologies</hi> to be Credited, is as <hi>Great a Sin,</hi> as the <hi>Heathens</hi> Sacrificing of their <hi>Children,</hi> to the <hi>Idol-Moloch.</hi> For ſuch Falſe Appeals, may ruin thouſands of <hi>Deluded Souls;</hi> cauſing them to Juſtifie the Wicked, and Condemn Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: Both which, are equally an <hi>Abomination to the Lord.</hi> It is very obſervable, in the 5th. of <hi>Numbers,</hi> the 15th. That in the <hi>Oblation</hi> made for Tryal of the ſuſpected Wiſe, there was <hi>No Oyl, nor Frankinſenſe,</hi> mixt with the Offering of Jealouſie. <hi>This ſignified,</hi> that while any Sinner gives the <hi>Lord</hi> cauſe, to ſuſpect the <hi>Chaſtity, and Loyalty of his Soul,</hi> in any Falſe Appeal; ſuch an <hi>Impudent Pretender</hi> unto Truth, <hi>(which ought to tye the Heart and Tongue, in the ſacred Bond of Chaſtity and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment)</hi> ſhall not go Unpuniſht. He cannot have any Hope of being <hi>Anoynted with the Spirit of Holineſs, and of Peace.</hi> His beſt Services, ſhall not be Received with any <hi>Mer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iful Interpertation;</hi> nor can the Prayers of ſuch, <hi>yield any Delightful Savor to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98865:16"/>the Lord;</hi> becauſe they cannot be mixt with the <hi>Fragrant Incenſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Interceſſion. This Advocate, ſhall rather turn the <hi>Edge of his juſt Indignation againſt them:</hi> Yea, by degrees, ſuch Sinners will <hi>Commence</hi> from <hi>Lying Equivocations,</hi> to down-right <hi>Perjurious Atheiſm,</hi> and the ſcoffing at all <hi>Religious Fear of Damnation,</hi> to all Eternity. Apologies <hi>artificially</hi> contrived, neither cover the <hi>Scandal</hi> of the Sin, nor <hi>Cure</hi> or <hi>Recover</hi> the Sinner. They are rather Libelling Accuſations againſt <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Juſtice,</hi> who hath <hi>found out</hi> the Hypocrite, in his <hi>Atheiſtial Preſumption</hi> of <hi>Impunity.</hi> Such Self-Defences, rather <hi>aggravate</hi> Guilt, than <hi>waſh</hi> away the <hi>Stain of Sin, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ingenuouſly to Confeſs the Crime laid to our Charge, and proved upon us, is the <hi>only Honorable Apology,</hi> and not any <hi>Sordid Yielding up of the Cauſe. Judah</hi>'s Name, which ſignifyed to give Praiſe to <hi>God</hi> by Confeſſion of Sin, was made good by his Practice, in the Caſe of <hi>Thamar.</hi> A <hi>True Penitentiaries</hi> Heart, is <hi>Grieved for</hi> his Offence, and not <hi>Imbittered againſt</hi> any Adverſary, for Charging It <hi>Home</hi> upon him. Thus, by Ingenuity, <hi>we prevent</hi> the Judgment, and ſeverer Condemnation of the <hi>Lord.</hi> He will never <hi>Reject ſuch,</hi> who will put themſelves to <hi>Shame;</hi> but will then be moſt <hi>pacifyed,</hi> when they leaſt <hi>ſpare Themſelves.</hi> At <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Tribunal, to Juſtify ones Self, is to <hi>Loſe the Cauſe,</hi> and more <hi>incenſe</hi> the Judge of all the World. <hi>There,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Appealers ſhall neither be able to <hi>Conceal,</hi> nor to <hi>Deny</hi> their Crimes. <hi>Then,</hi> they ſhall not <hi>Defend</hi> themſelves, much leſs, <hi>Glory</hi> in their Shame. A free Peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Confeſſion, Reconciles <hi>God</hi> to the Sinner; and the Sinner to <hi>Himſelf,</hi> in the Recovery of his Loſt <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Reputation.</hi> Yea, it is attended with the Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Eſſicacy of Faith;</hi> not only in applying the Merit and Vertue of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Blood,</hi> ſhed for the <hi>Expiation of Guilt;</hi> but it alſo obtains <hi>Singular Remarks of Divine Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor.</hi> I ſhall inſtance <hi>This,</hi> in a Miniſter; who once joyned with others of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, in Ejecting <hi>Satan</hi> out of one Poſſeſt. <hi>Satan</hi> being <hi>loath</hi> to be diſturbed or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, deſigned to <hi>diſcourage</hi> this Miniſter, by ſuggeſting to the poſſeſt Perſon, that he was formerly of a <hi>Scandalous Converſation;</hi> whereof the <hi>Daemoniack</hi> Accuſed him <hi>before</hi> All who were preſent. The Faithful Servant of the moſt <hi>High God, acknowledged</hi> all thoſe Crimes laid to his Charge, and took the <hi>Shame of them</hi> to Himſelf; thereby giving <hi>Glory</hi> to the Lord. Hereupon, he grew <hi>more Confident,</hi> that the <hi>Lord</hi> would ſignally Honor him, as an Inſtrument to Eject <hi>Satan</hi> out of the Poſſeſt Perſon. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, he ſet himſelf more humbly and fervently to Pray; and in the very time of the Duty, the <hi>Devil</hi> flew out of his Long loved Tennement; ſo that, the <hi>Daemoniack</hi> was not longer Tormented by him. If theſe <hi>Jeſuits</hi> had been as <hi>Ingenuous Confiten<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> as they had been <hi>Buſie Confeſſors,</hi> in <hi>racking</hi> other Mens Conſciences; This <hi>it ſelf,</hi> had been a <hi>Miracle.</hi> But they <hi>Dye</hi> in the ſame Impoſtures, which they promote while they <hi>Live.</hi> Their Religion, <hi>(as they have moulded it to Secular Intereſt)</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a Cheat, <hi>Varniſht over</hi> with Specious Shews of <hi>Piety:</hi> It is only a <hi>Fardle of Lyes</hi> ſubtilly packt together, and the <hi>Dead-Sea</hi> of all abominable <hi>Impieties.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, no wonder, if ſuch who avowedly profeſs the <hi>Trade</hi> of <hi>Seduction,</hi> are as Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous at the <hi>Art of Equivocation.</hi> Hence it is, that they Obſtinately and Impudently <hi>ſport Themſelves,</hi> in maintaining that <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> againſt all Right Reaſon, and Self-Conviction. While they draw all Appeals to the <hi>Pope, as Infallible,</hi> they preſume, that He can <hi>ſuperſede</hi> the Righteous Judgment of the ſupreme <hi>Majeſty</hi> of Heaven, in delivering of them from the <hi>Curſe</hi> of their Falſe Appeals.</p>
            <p>All the fore-going Conſiderations being well weighed, the Self-Imprecating Appeals of theſe <hi>Jeſuits, If they were not as Innocent as the Child <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nborn,</hi> needed not ſtagger any Perſon, concerning the Juſtice of their Condemnation and Execution. For, <hi>that Form</hi> of their Canting Plea, which very probably, was <hi>preſcribed</hi> to them, or <hi>fore-agreed to</hi> among themſelves, without any Alteration, may be <hi>thus</hi> Unriddled; <hi>viz.</hi> I can no more <hi>Proteſt</hi> my Innocency, than the <hi>Child <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nborn can.</hi> I cannot <hi>Really</hi> do it; though in Artificial Words I may <hi>Endeavour</hi> it. Or <hi>Thus:</hi> The Child Unborn is <hi>Really In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent,</hi> but cannot <hi>Proteſt</hi> it. I <hi>may</hi> and <hi>do</hi> proteſt it; yet have it <hi>not Really</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt: Nor is the Child Unborn <hi>really</hi> Innocent. <hi>True,</hi> It cannot be Charged with any Injurious <hi>Fact;</hi> yet, <hi>is It not Innocent,</hi> becauſe <hi>the Rectitude of Human Nature, or that Original Righteouſneſs, which ought to be in It, by the Law of its Primitive Creation in</hi> Adam, <hi>the Root and Common Truſtee of Perfect Righteouſneſs, for his Poſterity, is by his Apoſtacy, juſtly wanting in every Child.</hi> There is in the Nature of the Child Unborn, a <hi>Seminal</hi> Averſneſs to <hi>God,</hi> and a <hi>Propenſneſs</hi> to all Evil. Therefore, to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That they were as Innocent as the Child Unborn, <hi>was as much as to ſay,</hi> That
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98865:17"/>
               <hi>They were Guilty before God;</hi> for, <hi>So is the Child <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nborn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, the <hi>Council of Trent</hi> hath Determined, (as an <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi>) That in <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> all the true and proper Nature of Original Sin, is quite aboliſht. Upon <hi>That account</hi> (<hi>They</hi> ſay) <hi>God himſelf, cannot bind any One to Repent of it any more, than of an Innocent, Harmleſs Thing.</hi> Council Trident. Seſſ. 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Soto ibid.</hi> So, theſe Malefactors, being now about to Receive (as they preſumed) the <hi>Baptiſm and Crown of Martyrdom,</hi> thought this would immediately <hi>waſh away</hi> the Guilt and Stayn of their Bloody Crimes; yea, <hi>Repair</hi> the Integrity and Peace of their Conſcience, after a <hi>Falſe</hi> avowing of their Innocency. Poſſibly, they reputed themſelves Innocent, becauſe they were Arraigned before a <hi>Proteſtant-Court</hi> of <hi>Judicature;</hi> which <hi>they</hi> counted <hi>Incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> to take Cognizance of their Crimes; and ſo were Innocent, in <hi>That</hi> Reſpect. Or, themſelves eſteemed It, a <hi>Meritorious Act,</hi> to <hi>Murther Hereticks.</hi> This <hi>De Graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiis</hi> proves, out of their <hi>Own Church-Laws.</hi> Graff. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>Numb.</hi> 12. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius</hi> alſo, <hi>Commends</hi> the Murthering of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as having Forfeited their Lives by the Sentence of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> pronounced againſt them Yearly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suarez,</hi> an Eminent Author, in the Fourth Chapter of his Sixth Book, againſt the King of <hi>Great-Britain,</hi> ſaith, That if the <hi>Pope</hi> Depoſes a <hi>King, without giving Expreſs Commiſſion to Kill him:</hi> In <hi>That</hi> Caſe (he Curſedly ſaith) It belongs only to his <hi>Lawful Succeſſor,</hi> if he be a <hi>Catholick;</hi> or, if <hi>He will not do it,</hi> then, it <hi>belongs to the Common People to do it.</hi> Yea generally, <hi>Bellarmine, Becanus, Francis de Verona, Ribadinera, Gretzer, Eudaemon-Johannes,</hi> and <hi>Emanuel Sa,</hi> (all which, amount to more than only <hi>Mariana,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Gawen</hi> untruly Alledged) Theſe maintain, <hi>That the</hi> Pope <hi>hath Power to Chaſtiſe (yea, Kill) Heretical Princes.</hi> From the Depoſition of <hi>Henry</hi> the 3d. by <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 5th. enſued the <hi>Parricide</hi> Committed by <hi>Jaques-Clement:</hi> For the which, the ſaid <hi>Pope</hi> gave <hi>Thanks</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> in open <hi>Conſiſtory.</hi> This <hi>Oration</hi> was Printed at <hi>Paris,</hi> by <hi>Nicholas Nivelle,</hi> and <hi>Rollin Thierri;</hi> with <hi>Approbation</hi> of three Doctors, <hi>viz. Boucher, De Creil,</hi> and <hi>Ancelin.</hi> Or (it may be) they pleaded their Integrity, becauſe they <hi>Acted by, and under the</hi> Pope's <hi>Commiſſion;</hi> who (as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) can <hi>Legitimate</hi> the worſt of Crimes, ſo as to make them become <hi>Real Virtues.</hi> This Aſſertion I believe no more, than I do <hi>that Rapper</hi> of the <hi>Popiſh Miracle,</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be wrought upon <hi>this</hi> Occaſion: A <hi>Polonian</hi> Gentleman, ſpeaking ſlightly of the <hi>Pope</hi> at Dinner among his Friends, the <hi>White-Bread</hi> next to him, became preſently as <hi>Black as Ink;</hi> But upon his Penitential Recanting, it turned <hi>Whiter than it was before.</hi> Thus their <hi>Appeals</hi> are of as much Credit, as their <hi>Fabulous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or, it may be, they Pleaded their Integrity, as their Holy Father, the <hi>Pope, aſſumes High Names of Sanctity;</hi> being himſelf of a <hi>clean Contrary</hi> Diſpoſition. Thus a <hi>Cruel Pope,</hi> takes the Title of <hi>Clement;</hi> and <hi>Malefacins,</hi> will needs pretend to be <hi>Boniface.</hi> This is to be Innocent, <hi>per Antiphraſin,</hi> by the Rule of Contraries.</p>
            <p>But, that it may not ſeem <hi>ſtrange,</hi> that Dying-Criminals will falſly avow their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency,</hi> my ſelf, in my late <hi>Experience,</hi> (as <hi>Ordinary</hi> of <hi>Newgate</hi>) have known ſome Malefactors Condemned for <hi>Murther</hi> and <hi>Burglaries,</hi> to have gone out of the World, with a <hi>Notorious</hi> Aſſerting of their Integrity; although they had twice or thrice Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to me, (with ſome ſeeming Remorſe) that they were juſtly Condemned for the ſaid Crimes.</p>
            <p>I do believe, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have been their <hi>Tutors, Patterns,</hi> and <hi>Patrons,</hi> in ſuch Abominable Untruths. I ſhall more <hi>cloſely</hi> Convince all Unbyaſſed Perſons, that theſe <hi>Five Jeſuits</hi> could not be Innocent. Their Witneſſes from St. <hi>Omers,</hi> were Votaries <hi>Trayn'd up</hi> in their Religion, and ſworn at their Entrance into the <hi>Colledge,</hi> to obey their Superiours Inſtructions. Therefore, ſome of them being askt by the <hi>Honorable Court</hi> of <hi>Judicature,</hi> What they could averr (as to their <hi>own Knowledge</hi>) about a very Material Queſtion? replyed, <hi>That they were not Inſtructed to Anſwer that Point:</hi> Which demonſtrates, <hi>that</hi> they were <hi>Fore-taught,</hi> as <hi>Parrots,</hi> what to alledge in <hi>other</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, to have invalidated Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> his Teſtimony: Yet were they Heard with <hi>Wonderful Patience and Candour.</hi> Nay, the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> themſelves, when they made their <hi>Own Defence,</hi> did offer nothing of any conſiderable weight, <hi>but meer Sophiſtical Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> why the <hi>Court</hi> ſhould not proceed to paſs Judgment upon them. At their Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, <hi>What Self-Imprecations</hi> did they uſe, as if they would by Theſe, <hi>as a Magical Conjuration, Charm the Publick Spectators,</hi> to give Credit to their Lying and <hi>Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Appeals.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98865:17"/>
            <p>Yet, theſe Diſturbers and Underminers of Human Society, before they were turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the World, thought it Neceſſary, to <hi>Charm the Secret-biting-Accuſations of their Conſciences,</hi> with Father <hi>Whitebread</hi>'s Abſolution, which they <hi>Received</hi> (in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability) when they <hi>Whiſpered</hi> together. This they Reſerved <hi>till Now,</hi> as a <hi>Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Purgation of all their Crimes,</hi> and as a <hi>Safe Ticket,</hi> or <hi>Tranſport unto Heaven.</hi> They counted <hi>Atheiſtical Lyes,</hi> to be St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Keys,</hi> to Open <hi>Paradiſe</hi> unto them; Or a moſt Dextrous <hi>Artificial Pick-lock,</hi> to ſcrew themſelves into a Good Opinion with the Credulous, Vulgar People. But, as <hi>that Witty</hi> Pope <hi>ſaid,</hi> (when he Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Holy-Water</hi> on <hi>Romiſh Novices,</hi> and they Expected <hi>Miraculous</hi> Effects) <hi>He who</hi> will be <hi>Deceived, let his Superſtitious Conceit be</hi> Rewarded with a Cheat: <hi>So ſay I;</hi> Let <hi>Papiſts</hi> be deluded with falſe Proteſtations, who believe a <hi>Religion, ſtufft with Lyes and Blaſphemies.</hi> But, let not any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> be ſo <hi>Infected,</hi> as to Reſigne their <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and Reſolve their <hi>Faith,</hi> into the Conduct of <hi>their bare</hi> Aſſertions; who Promote their Church, by all <hi>Deceivableneſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs.</hi> How are <hi>Popiſh Novices</hi> in a <hi>blind Zeal,</hi> hurryed on by ſuch Sophiſters, to perpetrate the moſt Notorious Aſſaſſinations of Princes; <hi>and not to Boggle at This;</hi> as if it were a Vertue highly Meritorious. Thus do ſuch Bigots <hi>gratify</hi> the Blood-thirſty Humor of the <hi>Scarlet Whore,</hi> and <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute</hi> the Fury of the <hi>Romiſh Beaſt.</hi> And yet, when <hi>Jeſuits</hi> are Juſtly put to Death for <hi>Villainous Treaſons,</hi> they dare proteſt, that they Dye <hi>Martyrs</hi> for the Cauſe of their Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus;</hi> whom they Crucify afreſh, not only by the Hands of an <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Maſs-Priest,</hi> but in the Perſecution of the Profeſſors of his <hi>pure Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will give ſome <hi>proof</hi> of this. <hi>Baron Hene,</hi> one of his Majeſtie's Juſticiaries in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> aſſured a Perſon of Honor, that one <hi>John Curphy,</hi> a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> Condemned for a <hi>Burglary,</hi> in the Year 1671. at the time of his Execution, did <hi>peremptorily Deny</hi> the Fact, and made ſolemn Appeals to <hi>God</hi> of his Innocency. Yet, the <hi>Contrary was thus Diſcovered:</hi> After he had Hung ſome little time, the <hi>Rope by Chance brake;</hi> ſo he fell down a little Stunned: Yet ſome <hi>Seed of Life</hi> remaining in him, he was brought to his perfect Speech. Hereupon, Terror was ſo deeply impreſt upon his Conſcience, <hi>for Lying,</hi> (though counted a <hi>Venial</hi> Sin before) that he was forced to Confeſs the Fact; and after ſome time given him for Repentance, he was Executed as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, that <hi>Impudent, Impenitent Malefactors,</hi> at different <hi>Seaſons,</hi> have dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent <hi>Sentiments</hi> of <hi>God</hi>'s Omniſcient Juſtice, for <hi>Forging</hi> Lies deliberately, to make the World believe, that they are Innocent. God <hi>is concerned,</hi> in the Honor of his Juſtice, to Vindicate his Omniſciency, in ſome <hi>ſtrange</hi> Diſcovery of ſuch Matchleſs <hi>Impoſtors;</hi> who can <hi>hardly Repent in the time of Dying.</hi> Indeed, it is not probable, they ſhould; who <hi>Entayl</hi> upon themſelves, a Voluntary Curſe, by their <hi>pertinacious</hi> Diſſimulation, and their <hi>Lying Artifices.</hi> Theſe Men, are of late, <hi>Commenced</hi> ſuch profound Doctors in all Treaſon, Rebellion, Cruelty, <hi>and what not,</hi> which may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Government, that they <hi>out-ſtrip</hi> all former Monſters of <hi>Impiety.</hi> Had this Unparellel'd Villainy been <hi>Effected,</hi> it would have been Celebrated for a Meritorious Act, in Contriving a <hi>Speedier and more Effectual Method,</hi> for the Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Perſwaſion.</p>
            <p>This, is not the <hi>Truly, Antient, Apoſtolical Faith;</hi> but a <hi>Muſhrom</hi> of Fancy, ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up, out of an Affectation of <hi>Superſtitious Novelty;</hi> and cheriſht or ſpred by the <hi>Bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Ambition</hi> of Earthly Pomp and Grandeur. How can any Man, who hath not quite Extinguiſht <hi>all Sparks of Reaſon and Ingenuity,</hi> Embrace <hi>ſuch a</hi> Religion; which any <hi>Idiot</hi> may be <hi>Aſhamed to Live in,</hi> and <hi>Afraid to Dye in?</hi> For, it is a Miſcellany of <hi>Blaſphemies,</hi> and all <hi>Abſurd</hi> Opinions; yea, of all <hi>Impieties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereby, it comes to paſs, <hi>that at laſt,</hi> they are not able to put any Difference 'twixt Light and Darkneſs, Truth and Falſhood; nor to diſtinguiſh Righteouſneſs, from Violence and Injuſtice; nor Piety it ſelf, from the Extremity of Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>I have done with the Diſcovery of the Falſeneſs of their Appeals: Let us now ſee, whether their <hi>Faith and Charity</hi> in Dying, were of any <hi>Better Stamp.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:98865:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> Jeſuits <hi>Falſe-Faith in Dying, Detected to be Fancy and Preſumption.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HOw many Falſe <hi>Martyrs</hi> hath the world afforded, who while they <hi>Courted</hi> Death, Sacrificed only a <hi>Sturdy</hi> Body to a <hi>Stubborn</hi> Mind, to keep up ſome <hi>Hereſy</hi> in Repute? <hi>Jeſuits</hi> count <hi>this,</hi> a brave Reſolution; yet, it flows from the Inconſiderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a <hi>Sleepy ſecure Conſcience.</hi> They <hi>weigh not the after-claps</hi> of Death, nor <hi>Dread</hi> the future Aſſizes of the Univerſal Judgment. Hypocrits, will as confidently, <hi>commit and commend</hi> their Spirits into the Hand and Boſom of Chriſt, as if they had been <hi>Waſht</hi> in his Blood, and <hi>changed</hi> into his Image. <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> who are a <hi>Faithleſs</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, cannot <hi>really</hi> make uſe of the Sheild of Faith, to <hi>Blunt</hi> the Sting of Death; or to <hi>Quench</hi> the Fiery Dartings of <hi>Deſpair</hi> into their Hearts. For, <hi>that</hi> Faith which they pretend to, is rather <hi>Carnal fancy and preſumption,</hi> than any well regulated <hi>Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> of their Souls to the Conduct of the Scriptures, as imbraced by a <hi>firm</hi> Belief, Such Reſignation flowing from a <hi>Right-bred</hi> Faith, is <hi>Divinely</hi> grounded on the Sacred Authority of God <hi>Alone,</hi> who is the Architype of Truth. But <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Scriptures to be a <hi>perfect</hi> Rule of Faith, and of the practicals of Chriſtian Self-denyal. If they eſteemed the Sacred Records, able to make the <hi>Man of God</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly wiſe unto Salvation, then Conſequently, they muſt needs be the <hi>ſtrongeſt and only Sheild,</hi> to overcome the <hi>Inordinate Love of</hi> Natural Life, and the <hi>Slaviſh fear</hi> of a Violent Ignominious Death. Such a frame can <hi>never</hi> be attained, unleſs the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Scriptures, which are <hi>Divine in</hi> their Original and Authority, be <hi>Aſſented to, and Imbraced with</hi> a Faith <hi>Divinely</hi> ſubjected to them. I muſt <hi>receive and defend</hi> Divine Truth to the very Death; not becauſe I believe it with an <hi>Humane</hi> Faith, as giving <hi>more credit to</hi> the Churches Tradition (which <hi>Conſignes</hi> the Scriptures to be Canonical) than to the Authority of <hi>Divine</hi> Revelation: If ſo, I ground my Faith for Eternal Life, upon an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertain</hi> Opinion, or <hi>at beſt,</hi> upon the Raſh and <hi>bold</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion of ſome <hi>Pope</hi> or Council, who <hi>ſay</hi> and <hi>unſay,</hi> Decree and Aboliſh the <hi>ſame</hi> Conſtitution in a Breath.</p>
               <p>Thus, the <hi>Jeſuits-Faith,</hi> which is meerly <hi>or chiefly Humane,</hi> in the very eſſence and formality of it, (becauſe the Church or <hi>Pope determines So, or So,</hi>) can never reach to the Spiritual <hi>pitch and excellency</hi> of that Divine Faith; which being grounded on the <hi>Sole Authority</hi> of Divine Revelation, can only <hi>Juſtify and Save</hi> a mans Soul, and Conſequently, can only afford <hi>true courage and comfort</hi> in Dying. But <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> never had their Hearts <hi>purified</hi> by believing, and obeying the Truths of Chriſt, <hi>as ſuch;</hi> for <hi>then,</hi> they would have their Affections <hi>more in Heaven:</hi> But ſpending their Converſation chiefly <hi>among Machivilians of their own Tribe and Order,</hi> to promote a Secular Intereſt, rather than to Subject themſelves to the <hi>Rules of the Bleſſed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> (whoſe name their Society <hi>Blaſphemouſly</hi> pretends to) they cannot have any Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimental Taſt of the <hi>powerful joys</hi> of the World to come. Their confidence therefore in Dying, cannot be <hi>Hearty and Ingenuous.</hi> It flows cheifly, from the <hi>Effort and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of natural courage,</hi> not from a <hi>Super-elevated</hi> Principle of Unfeigned Faith, which takes a <hi>proſpect</hi> of Eternal Life, not only beyond the <hi>pleaſing Accomodations and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages</hi> of this preſent World, but alſo, beyond the <hi>Torments</hi> of Death; that ſo God himſelf may be Glorified <hi>All in All,</hi> and not only a <hi>Saint-like</hi> Cannonization be Ambitiouſly aſpired unto, <hi>which,</hi> without <hi>real</hi> Holineſs, is but the <hi>Dream</hi> of a Fools-Paradiſe. Are not ſuch men under the deluſion <hi>of a ſtrange Phrency,</hi> and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually <hi>bewicht,</hi> who put <hi>on an Artificial</hi> courage and zeal, in ſealing a <hi>falſe</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with their Blood, only, out of a <hi>fond</hi> Ambition, to avoid Purgatory on the left hand, and that the <hi>Pope</hi> may immediately Canonize them <hi>for Heroical Champions,</hi> in defending the pride of his Tripple Crown. <hi>Jeſuits</hi> account this, to be <hi>juſtifying</hi> Faith to Eternal Life, firmly to <hi>Aſſont to</hi> all the <hi>Popes</hi> determinations as <hi>Infallible, when</hi> oftentimes, <hi>Popes</hi> have been perſons <hi>neither of common Truth nor Honeſty,</hi> but <hi>Atheiſts, Hereticks, Conjurers, Sodomites,</hi> yea <hi>Incarnate Devils. Platina</hi> in the Life of <hi>John</hi> the 13th. <hi>Conſtan. Concil. Seſſ.</hi> 11. <hi>Art.</hi> 5. <hi>Benedict.</hi> 9. <hi>vide Baronium anno,</hi> 1034. <hi>N.</hi> 3. Yet the unwritten Traditions, or <hi>Fancies rather,</hi> of theſe wicked Monſters, muſt be Imbraced as Objects of <hi>juſtifying</hi> Faith, by all ſuch, who expect <hi>not to be ſent</hi> to Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98865:18"/>when they Dye. But, Can <hi>Jeſuitical Martyrs,</hi> for the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>Religion,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a firm Belief, that they ſhall be <hi>Canonized for Saints?</hi> Yes. For <hi>Graffius, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi> and other Divines, have found out a <hi>compendious</hi> way to Salvation: For, by Forming the Signe of the Croſs <hi>with Three Fingers,</hi> to ſignify the Myſtery of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Trinity:</hi> by drawing the Croſs from the <hi>Fore-head to the Navel,</hi> to ſignify, that the Son of <hi>God</hi> Deſcended from Heaven into the Bowels of his <hi>Mother;</hi> and then drawing the Croſs line from the Left-Arm to the Right; Hereby the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation</hi> is Expreſt; <hi>viz. Chriſt</hi> came from Heaven to Earth, that we who had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be placed amongſt the <hi>Goats</hi> at his Left-hand, might be removed to his Right-hand, amongſt the <hi>Sheep.</hi> Behold! What Myſteries of Faith, <hi>Mother Church</hi> hath taught Her Eldeſt Sons, yea, all her Novices; that by theſe <hi>Exact Moods</hi> of Form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Croſs, <hi>without the Knowledge of any thing beſides,</hi> even this <hi>alone,</hi> may be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for Salvation. This is <hi>All</hi> the Faith, neceſſary for a <hi>Roman Catholick;</hi> and when by ſuch Admirable Conduct of the Croſs, he hath <hi>but Once</hi> believed, he need <hi>never more trouble Himſelf</hi> with Faith, while he Lives. So <hi>Bonacina Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>in</hi> 1. <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. Diſp.</hi> 3. <hi>Q.</hi> 2. <hi>N.</hi> 16. <hi>Graff. Deciſ. Part</hi> 1. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 24. <hi>N.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>You have ſeen the Admirable Efficacy of a <hi>Jeſuits Faith,</hi> in Signing himſelf, <hi>when Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> with the Sign of the <hi>Croſs:</hi> Now view the Effects of their <hi>Hopes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> Hopes of Divine Mercy and Salvation, at Death, Detected to be Falſe, and Vain.</head>
               <p>ALL <hi>Rational</hi> Hope of Salvation, is <hi>Divine</hi> in its Original and Foundation; this will not make <hi>them Aſhamed,</hi> who are Poſſeſt of it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. It is not like the <hi>Spiders-Web,</hi> becauſe it hath <hi>God in Chriſt, for its Foundation.</hi> 1 Col. 27. <hi>Chriſt in You, the Hope of Glory.</hi> But now, <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctrine is <hi>oppoſite</hi> to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in all his <hi>Offices,</hi> as making him to be an <hi>Inſufficient Saviour.</hi> Thus they joyn <hi>Pennances,</hi> as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Additions to <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Infinite Satisfaction for Sin, as if he had Merited, to take away only the <hi>Fault or Offence;</hi> and had left the Sinner <hi>himſelf,</hi> to compleat the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of his Soul, by ſatisfying for the <hi>puniſhment of Sin,</hi> in <hi>Self-invented</hi> and <hi>Self-impoſed</hi> Severities, upon the Body. How doth this <hi>derogate</hi> from <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Infinite Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming Love, in making a <hi>full</hi> and <hi>perfect</hi> Satisfaction for All Sin, and the Appur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances thereof, in reſpect of Perſons truly Juſtifyed. <hi>Beſides, Romiſh</hi> Doctrine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-throws another part of the Foundation of <hi>true Chriſtian Hope,</hi> which is, the <hi>Alone All-ſufficiency</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Meritorious Interceſſion:</hi> Thus they joyn with <hi>Him, Suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> and <hi>Coadjutors,</hi> in <hi>this</hi> part of his Prieſtly Office; as if Himſelf were not a <hi>pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and faithful High-prieſt, as God-man, ſolely and ſufficiently prevalent with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> to Obtain whatever we can <hi>Ask,</hi> according to <hi>His Will.</hi> But Papiſts <hi>pray amiſs to Saints and Angels;</hi> who know not their <hi>particular</hi> Diſtreſſes, nor the Thoughts of the <hi>Heart,</hi> which Aſcend to <hi>God</hi> directly in Prayer: He only, can Hear the Suppll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of <hi>Millions,</hi> at the <hi>ſame</hi> time; and Supply the Wants of <hi>All Creatures.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they are <hi>Guilty</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> in their Orlſons: And, Can ſuch <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledgious Derogation</hi> from <hi>God</hi>'s Honor, ground any <hi>real</hi> Hope of being Heard, or Supplyed with the Neceſſary Means of Salvation? So far are <hi>ſuch Prayers,</hi> from giving the leaſt Hope of Eternal Life.</p>
               <p n="2">2. True <hi>Hope,</hi> hath the <hi>Promiſes of Free-Grace in Chriſt,</hi> for its Support: which Promiſes are only <hi>Yea, and Amen, in Him,</hi> to Chriſtians that are ſincere in their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. But, <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctors aſſert, that the <hi>Higheſt or moſt Neceſſary</hi> Duties of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, are only <hi>Counſels,</hi> which they are at Liberty to imbrace, or not; ſo as to make them <hi>practical.</hi> Thus they <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with the Neceſſary Duties of Religion; in which, the very <hi>Eſſence, Life,</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of it conſiſts: As they <hi>fancy</hi> Divine Precepts to be but <hi>Arbitrary Duties;</hi> ſo, <hi>to ſuch,</hi> Chriſt's Promiſes of Eternal Life, become as <hi>meer Cyphers,</hi> becauſe they do <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with his Laws, <hi>when,</hi> and <hi>as</hi> themſelves pleaſe to be <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> in their Obedience. <hi>That only</hi> is a Lively Hope of Salvation, which makes the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of it, to puriſy their Hearts, as <hi>God</hi> is Pure; which is <hi>fruitful</hi> in Obedience, and <hi>active</hi> in the wayes of Holineſs; which <hi>Girds up the Loyns of the Mind,</hi> by <hi>avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> all Impediments, and <hi>making uſe of all Expedients</hi> in the Chriſtian-Race; thus the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98865:19"/>Hope of <hi>ſeeing and enjoying God,</hi> doth ſtrenuouſly work <hi>up</hi> the Heart, to a <hi>Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in Holyneſs. Such an Hope <hi>only,</hi> can <hi>be a firm Anchor in all Extremities.</hi> But <hi>Popiſh</hi> Hopes (as the <hi>Spiders-Web</hi>) are ſoon ſwept away like <hi>Vanity:</hi> Yea, there is no Hope of Remedy, to <hi>Recover ſuch</hi> to a Salvable State, who <hi>ſtudy</hi> to be Ignorant, and fear to know the <hi>Latitude</hi> of <hi>God</hi>'s Will, leſt they ſhould be <hi>Obliged</hi> to follow it. How <hi>dangerous</hi> is an Implicite Faith! <hi>viz.</hi> to believe <hi>Only</hi> as the Church dictates, though ſhe teach Points <hi>contrary</hi> to the Purity of the Chriſtian-Inſtitution? How can <hi>that</hi> Faith, which is grounded on the Authority of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and conſequently, which is <hi>meerly Human,</hi> as <hi>moulded to his Determination,</hi> produce any <hi>ſolid</hi> Hope of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life? <hi>Hope</hi> is the Daughter, or Twin-Siſter of <hi>Faith:</hi> Therefore, <hi>As the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of This is,</hi> ſo <hi>Hope</hi> is True or Falſe. Such <hi>blind Bigots,</hi> who <hi>hold</hi> their Souls in this Miſerable Captivity, cannot <hi>rationally</hi> think them Redeemed by the Blood of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> while they <hi>reject</hi> that Saving Light which is offered to them. <hi>What then</hi> ſhall we think of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> who ſin <hi>againſt</hi> Conviction, that they may <hi>uphold</hi> a Carnal Intereſt? If any <hi>perſiſt</hi> in This, they Sin <hi>damnably,</hi> and cannot have any <hi>real</hi> Hope of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The like we may affirm of <hi>ſuch,</hi> who, to Preſerve their <hi>Trading and Worldly Accommodations</hi> in <hi>Popiſh</hi> Countries, quench the Sparks of True Convictions in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Theſe Perſons are <hi>Aſhamed or Afraid</hi> to Confeſs <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>intire Truth,</hi> in the <hi>Purity thereof</hi> againſt all <hi>Romiſh forged Innovations,</hi> although <hi>Theſe</hi> betray Men's Souls inſenſibly to Perdition <hi>Such perſons,</hi> who for <hi>State-Intereſt, viz.</hi> to gain <hi>Favour or Wealth,</hi> ſuppreſs the Sentiments of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s pure Religion, and receive the Mark of the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> though not in the <hi>Fore-head</hi> openly, yet cloſely in their <hi>Hand;</hi> This <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> may juſtly take hold of them, that they ſhall be blinded and hardned to believe <hi>Romiſh</hi> Lies, according to that Juſt Sentence, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.11. That <hi>They all may be Damned, who Believe not the Truth once profeſt,</hi> but Reject it: Or refuſe to be <hi>informed</hi> of the Danger of <hi>Heretical Tenets,</hi> when <hi>Means of Conviction</hi> are offered; becauſe, they Demonſtrate hereby, <hi>That they have Pleaſure in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs.</hi> Now, Popiſh Religion is the <hi>Greateſt Seminary</hi> of Viciouſneſs, and all Impiety: For, Doth not the <hi>Council of Trent</hi> Eſtabliſh this, That Attrition <hi>only,</hi> which is but a <hi>ſlight</hi> Grief for Sin, from meer <hi>ſlaviſh Fear of Hell,</hi> or <hi>Shame,</hi> without any <hi>Love to God,</hi> is a <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient</hi> Demonſtration of Repentance to Eternal Life; ſo <hi>that the Sacrament of Penance be joyned with it?</hi> Yet this Sacrament of Penance, on <hi>which</hi> they ſay, the ſtreſs of Sinners Salvation depends, is a meer <hi>Human Invention: God</hi> hath <hi>promiſed</hi> nothing to it, upon <hi>Popiſh</hi> Terms; neither can a Man build any <hi>rational</hi> Hope upon It, that it will ſecure him from Damnation. They affirm, That the Sacrament of Penance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes <hi>All ſaving Graces,</hi> when Men are <hi>Dying:</hi> This is a <hi>Rare Device, by which</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucht Perſons may eſcape <hi>Hell</hi> at laſt, without True Repentance. There was never any <hi>Hereſie</hi> more <hi>monſtrous and pernitious,</hi> than this of the <hi>Trent-Council,</hi> which makes all Sins <hi>Safe,</hi> and all Duties <hi>Needleſs,</hi> by a Knack of very <hi>Eaſy</hi> Uſe, and <hi>New</hi> Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz. Abſolution,</hi> upon the meer Profeſſion of any <hi>ſlight</hi> Grief for Sin, though the Motive be but <hi>Natural,</hi> and the Grief it ſelf, in the next Degree to <hi>Nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Premiſes conſidered, I cannot ſee how Papiſts can rightly Ground their Hopes for Salvation, which is to be attained by Faith in <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone, as it purifyes the Heart to an Obediential Hope of Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> Charity Counterfeit in Life and Death.</head>
               <p>I Do ſuſpect, the <hi>Jeſuits Charity</hi> in Dying, could be no <hi>Better</hi> than their <hi>Faith:</hi> For, according to the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> of This, (which is the <hi>firſt</hi> Radical Grace Implanted) is <hi>proportionably,</hi> the Genuine Nature and Extenſion of Chriſtian Love. Now, if the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Faith be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſound</hi> (as I have Demonſtrated) I cannot ſee any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why their <hi>Charity</hi> ſhould be of the <hi>right Scriptural-ſtamp:</hi> How could theſe Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits <hi>ſincerely</hi> Forgive their Enemies? Is Self-denyal, this <hi>Grand Maſter-piece of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> ſo <hi>eaſily</hi> practiſed by Anti-Chriſtian Spirits? Yet, they would make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that they <hi>heartily</hi> Forgave their Enemies, as <hi>themſelves expected</hi> Forgiveneſs from <hi>God.</hi> But ſuch <hi>Sophiſters</hi> uſe to Forgive their Juſt Accuſers in a <hi>Complement,</hi> as they believe themſelves to be Forgiven of God <hi>in a Dream.</hi> I ſuſpect, that their Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation to their Adverſaries, was as <hi>Myſtical,</hi> as their Faith is <hi>Dubious.</hi> For, if they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98865:19"/>require an <hi>Implicite Faith only,</hi> to believe whatever the Church <hi>Virtual, viz,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> dictates; why ſhould their Charity be more <hi>expreſſive and diſtinct, viz.</hi> in Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending ſuch Perſons, who <hi>deſignedly</hi> (as themſelves aſſerted) ſought to take away their Lives.</p>
               <p>Is <hi>This</hi> the Charity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, to Condemn all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to <hi>Hell;</hi> while in a <hi>fond-miſtaken</hi> Compaſſion, all Her <hi>Own Faction,</hi> (though never ſo <hi>prodigiouſly</hi> Wicked) are Canonized for Saints? Yea, Why doth the <hi>Pope,</hi> that <hi>Merciful High prieſt,</hi> permit ſo many Souls to lye <hi>broyling</hi> in <hi>Purgatorian</hi> Flames, when he ought with a more <hi>fervent</hi> Charity, and at a more <hi>eaſie price,</hi> to Redeem them <hi>thence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How could theſe <hi>Jeſuits</hi> ſincerely Forgive their Enemies, who fancy a ſtrange <hi>Mock-Forgiveneſs</hi> of a Sinner, by the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Truth.</hi> This they do, to <hi>colour and palltate</hi> their own Hypocritical Reconciliation. Their Blaſphemy is <hi>this:</hi> That <hi>God</hi> in Pardoning Sinners, forgives the <hi>Offence,</hi> but not the <hi>Puniſhment. This</hi> muſt be ſatisfyed <hi>For, In,</hi> and <hi>By</hi> Themſelves. This makes way for <hi>fraudulent</hi> Reconciliations: For, the Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Perſon may alledge the <hi>Example of God Himſelf;</hi> who, while he pretends to <hi>Remit</hi> an Injury, yet <hi>Reſerves</hi> in his Heart, <hi>Seeds</hi> of Wrath for a Crop of Future Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. For, he will ſay, <hi>Would you have me more Merciful than God! Herein,</hi> I have followed <hi>His Example.</hi> We are too much inclined to <hi>Revenge;</hi> we need not <hi>ſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices,</hi> to prove, that God <hi>Invites us</hi> there unto. Theſe Men pretend <hi>Meekneſs of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> but it is <hi>Malice</hi> Raked up in <hi>Embers,</hi> till they find a <hi>fit</hi> Opportunity to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged <hi>in Earneſt,</hi> and with a <hi>fuller Intereſt.</hi> I cannot ſee thorow the <hi>Miſts</hi> of their <hi>Impoſtures;</hi> nor can I Reconcile their <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Words</hi> together, when almoſt in the <hi>ſame</hi> Breath, they Revile and Condemn their Judges of Injuſtice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Virtually,</hi> they Supplicated for the <hi>Avenging</hi> of their Blood, as wrongfully ſpilt; while in thoſe <hi>very Appeals</hi> which they made to God, they aſſerted themſelves to be as White and Innocent, as Innocency it ſelf. I have Read of <hi>Apollonius Thyanaeus,</hi> that when he Pray'd, he had his Sword lying <hi>drawn</hi> before him, as <hi>ready</hi> to take Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on his Enemies; though this were the <hi>only</hi> Expedient, to cut off Mercy from himſelf. Do not <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctors maintain, That it is Lawful to <hi>Kill</hi> any one who only <hi>Reviles us? This,</hi> they count not Revenge, but a <hi>Regular Self-Love,</hi> yea, a very <hi>Juſt Care,</hi> which the Injured Perſon <hi>Owes</hi> unto Himſelf. At the Leaſt, he may Repair his Honor, by the Swords-point of Recrimination. Doubtleſs, they who hold, That we owe <hi>No Expreſs Act</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> to God Himſelf, all our Life-long; and that the Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>Deſire only</hi> of Loving Him (when we are <hi>Dying</hi>) <hi>fulfils</hi> our Duty in this Reſpect, could have but Little or <hi>No</hi> Charity, for their Enemies. This is really the Merciful Temper of <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> to wiſh, That <hi>by One Blow</hi> in the Deſtruction of His Majeſty, they had <hi>readily</hi> diſpatcht Three Nations, becauſe they will not ſtoop to the Yoke of <hi>Anti-Chriſtian</hi> Hereſie and Tyranny.</p>
               <p>How <hi>Diabolically</hi> did theſe Malefactors preſume to Clear themſelves, by clapping One Lye <hi>gravely</hi> upon Another. Firſt, They aſſerted their <hi>Innocency,</hi> though <hi>Convicted</hi> and Righteouſly Condemned. Then, to teſtify their Innocence by their Meekneſs, they pretended to Forgive their Enemies; while by a Jeſuitical Back Blow, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſtab their <hi>Reputation,</hi> and Invalidate their Teſtimony by <hi>falſe</hi> Recrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations. Now, it is <hi>alike Abſurd,</hi> for a Malefactor <hi>convicted</hi> by Law, to preſume to Clear himſelf, by Calumniating of another; as for one <hi>really</hi> Innocent, to bear a <hi>Falſe</hi> Teſtimony againſt himſelf. This is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural,</hi> and againſt Regular <hi>Self-Love;</hi> but the Other is <hi>Natural</hi> to a Corrupt Heart, though it be <hi>Diabolical.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will prove the <hi>Abſurdity</hi> of the Firſt-mentioned Artifice, by inſtancing in a True Example of the Latter; <hi>viz.</hi> An Innocent Woman bore falſe Witneſs againſt Her ſelf, that ſhe was the <hi>proper</hi> Murtherer of a Child, which was deſtroyed by its <hi>own</hi> Mother. The <hi>Devil</hi> ſuggeſted to this <hi>feign'd</hi> Criminal, that it was impoſſible, ſhe could have a <hi>broken</hi> Heart for Sin, unleſs ſhe were publickly Hanged, and. <hi>ſo ſhamed</hi> into a Penitential Frame. The Woman <hi>cloſed</hi> with this Self-cruel Deſign, Indicted her ſelf, and Pleaded <hi>Guilty</hi> of the Murther: But the Judge obſerving her <hi>modeſt</hi> and <hi>penitential</hi> Behaviour, could not think, that ſhe was the <hi>Real</hi> Murtherer. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he urged her, not <hi>wilfully</hi> to caſt away her own Life, by <hi>palliating and p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonating</hi> of anothers Crime. She frequently <hi>affirmed,</hi> that ſhe Killed the Child. Yet at laſt, <hi>God</hi> was pleaſed to diſcover <hi>Satan</hi>'s <hi>Stratagem.</hi> So the Mother, who was the <hi>proper</hi>-Criminal, was ſought for, and Apprehended; but the <hi>Other</hi> was ſet at Liberty, with ſome <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>buke</hi> and <hi>Pity</hi> of her Folly. This <hi>ſtrange</hi> Occurrence, a Perſon wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Credit, Related to my ſelf, upon his <hi>own</hi> Knowledge, as he <hi>attended</hi> the Iudge in his Circuit.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98865:20"/>
               <p>Now, Why is it not probable, that the <hi>Devil</hi> might as <hi>deſignedly,</hi> Animate theſe <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits,</hi> to aſſert their <hi>own</hi> Innocency, by <hi>darting</hi> Calumniations againſt their upright Witneſſes, to Confirm them in their Impenitency. The Charity of theſe Jeſuits, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Enemies, is the more to be <hi>ſuſpected,</hi> becauſe their <hi>Caſuiſtical Divines</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that a Criminal may <hi>lawfully</hi> Perjurate himſelf, in pleading of his Innocency; yea, may without Sin, falſly Recriminate, and Murder ſuch Witneſſes, who are <hi>likely to prove</hi> the Crime againſt Him.</p>
               <p>This is their <hi>common</hi> Doctrine, <hi>Bannes</hi> 22 <hi>Q.</hi> 70 <hi>Art.</hi> 3 <hi>pag.</hi> Thus <hi>Bolſec,</hi> and <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleius,</hi> did caſt out <hi>Falſe</hi> Aſperſions, to deſame <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> that Credit might not be given to their Writings againſt the <hi>Roman</hi>-Church. <hi>Ledeſma,</hi> a <hi>Dominican,</hi> aſſures us, that to Defame <hi>falſly</hi> any Adverſary, is no Sin: For, it is the Common Doctrine of <hi>Aquinas</hi> his Diſciples. <hi>Caramuel</hi> ſayes, <hi>Twenty</hi> Doctors aſſert it Lawful. If <hi>Popiſh</hi> Confitents will be Prodigal of their <hi>own</hi> Reputation, and (out of a <hi>Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Fear</hi> of loſing the Benefit of Abſolution, if they Enumerate not <hi>punctually</hi> all their Sins) will Charge themſelves with ſuch Wickedneſs, which they never Committed: How <hi>little</hi> Conſcience will Jeſuited Perſons make, of Murthering not only the <hi>Good Name,</hi> but the <hi>Perſon</hi> alſo, of an upright Witneſs; that ſo they may <hi>prevent</hi> a True Teſtimony againſt them, or <hi>weaken</hi> the Validity of it.</p>
               <p>By this Maxime, which Legitimats falſe Deſamations, the grand Sophiſters in that <hi>Helliſh Art,</hi> have ſet themſelves upon a Pillory of Infamy, with this <hi>Inſcription,</hi> That they are <hi>never</hi> to be Credited, though they Imprecate themſelves, if they ſpeak not Truth. Yet, theſe are the Perſons, who would be <hi>Admired</hi> for their <hi>Self-Denyal,</hi> in <hi>Forgiving</hi> of their Enemies. This is of <hi>kind</hi> to the <hi>Blind prepoſterous Charity</hi> of their <hi>Popes,</hi> who often Canonize for Saints and Martyrs, ſuch who are Executed for Treaſon and Rebellion. Yet <hi>Cotton</hi> ſayes, in the 26th. Chap. of 1ſt. Book of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> That to <hi>doubt</hi> of the Bleſſedneſs of <hi>ſuch</hi> Canonized Saints, is to make a <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge againſt</hi> the Book of <hi>Predeſtination;</hi> which the <hi>Pope</hi> (as <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Vicar) hath the <hi>Keeping and Opening of,</hi> though it be ſealed up from the Knowledge of all <hi>Hereticks.</hi> What a <hi>blaſphemous</hi> Charity is this, to Arrogate the Diſpoſal of the <hi>Book of Eternal Life?</hi> For, Who can think, that <hi>Popes</hi> have a Right to inrole whom they will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Saints,</hi> when our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> affirm, that many of <hi>Their Holyneſſes</hi> are Damn'd <hi>themſelves?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us now ſee, whether the <hi>Jeſuits Courage, and Chearfulneſs,</hi> in Dying for their <hi>Religious Treaſons,</hi> be of any better Stamp, than their <hi>Diſſembled Charity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Jeſuitical Courage</hi> and <hi>Chearfulneſs</hi> in Dying for <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie</hi> and <hi>Treaſon,</hi> how Differenced from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of <hi>Real MARTYRS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Object. <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t is it likely, that ſuch</hi> Holy Men <hi>ſhould put on a</hi> Diſſembled Courage <hi>and</hi> Chearfulneſs, <hi>in Dying for Hereſie or Treaſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I Anſwer; Although this is the <hi>Worſt ſort</hi> of Lying, becauſe it Counterfeits the <hi>Anoynting of God</hi>'s <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> and <hi>ſtains</hi> the Glory of their <hi>Reputed</hi> Martyrdom; yet, I ſhall demonſtrate, that Diſſimulation in <hi>this</hi> kind, is not only <hi>poſſible,</hi> but frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Exerciſed.</p>
               <p>Erroneous Principles may have ſuch a Prevalency upon the Conſcience and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>Traytors,</hi> as to raiſe a Paſſionate <hi>Falſe</hi> Joy, in Suffering a <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and Ignominious Death.</hi> But, How doth this <hi>ſtrange Witch-Craft,</hi> differ from the <hi>Real</hi> Joy of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Martyrs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. True Chearfulneſs in Suffering, differs in the <hi>Spring-head,</hi> or <hi>Root:</hi> There is a <hi>Gracious,</hi> and a <hi>Moral</hi> Kind of Sincerity. Now, from this <hi>Moral</hi> Inducement <hi>only,</hi> meer Opinioniſts will Do and Suffer <hi>much,</hi> that they may preſerve the Peace of an <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Conſcience</hi> in being <hi>Honeſt</hi> to their Falſe Light. Yet, do they not enjoy the Comfort of a Renewed Conſcience: This <hi>prefers</hi> the Glory of <hi>God,</hi> and the Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the <hi>Truth,</hi> before the Preſervation of its <hi>own</hi> Peace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Jeſuitical Courage,</hi> is <hi>Artificial and Forced,</hi> meerly out of <hi>deſigne,</hi> to keep up the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98865:20"/>
                  <hi>credit,</hi> of a Falſe Opinion; rather than any Hearty Demonſtration of Real <hi>Self-De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal.</hi> It ſpends it ſelf in Vain-Glory, and is not attended with any <hi>Humble Diſtruſt</hi> of Perſevering. <hi>Impoſtors,</hi> in their pretended Comfort, are either <hi>Beſotted</hi> with Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, or <hi>Tickled</hi> with Phantaſtick Joy. It is no wonder, if they ſuffer <hi>out of a Brain-ſick Fancy,</hi> for the <hi>Brats</hi> of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Superſtition. But <hi>Fancies</hi> in the Head, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get only <hi>Flaſhes</hi> of falſe Zeal and Comfort, by the Concitation of <hi>Brisk Animal</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. Thus, <hi>Phrentick</hi> Perſons (the Brain being <hi>over-heat</hi>) <hi>Cant,</hi> in ratling of their Chains, as if they were <hi>Princes</hi> in their own Imagination. <hi>Impoſtors</hi> ſuffer, either from the Strength of <hi>Deluſion,</hi> or from <hi>Stiffneſs</hi> and <hi>Rigidneſs</hi> of <hi>Spirit,</hi> becauſe they hold it a Diſcredit, to be <hi>Changlings</hi> in Opinion. But one <hi>Divinely</hi> Couragious for the Truth, chuſes rather to be Its <hi>Captive,</hi> than the <hi>Champion</hi> of Error.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Impoſtors</hi> cover a <hi>ſad peeviſh</hi> Heart, with a <hi>jocund</hi> Countenance: But <hi>real</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, having the <hi>ſecret</hi> Conſolations of <hi>God</hi>'s Spirit, are not Tranſported with <hi>Aiery</hi> Joys, neither are they <hi>Theatrical</hi> in their Carriage. Joy in the Holy Ghoſt (not in <hi>Fancy,</hi> or the <hi>Face</hi> only) reſts upon them. <hi>Res eſt Severa, Verum Gaudium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Diſſembled Courage,</hi> cannot be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform</hi> in a <hi>conſtant</hi> Undauntedneſs; <hi>viz. Such,</hi> which <hi>becalms</hi> the Paſſions, and <hi>confirms</hi> the Sufferer in his Uprightneſs. But ſome <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> have uſed <hi>Opiate Potions,</hi> that they might bring a <hi>Stupefaction</hi> on the Animal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, ſo as to have Little or <hi>No Senſation</hi> of their Death. But <hi>real</hi> Martyrs, refuſe to uſe any <hi>Artificial, Sinful Means,</hi> to <hi>force</hi> Joy, rather than to <hi>wait for it</hi> from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by the Acting of a Regular <hi>Faith.</hi> A <hi>Pſeudo-Martyrs</hi> Courage, is deſigned to Hector <hi>Proteſtants</hi> into a <hi>Belief</hi> of their Cheats; and their <hi>Patience</hi> is as Counterfeit, as their <hi>Penitence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. True <hi>Courage</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Martyrs, <hi>Convinces, Shames;</hi> and <hi>Converts</hi> ſome of their <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> becauſe the Lord ſets an <hi>edge</hi> on that Comfort which flows from <hi>His Spirit,</hi> rather than the Gallantry of a <hi>Roman</hi> Reſolution. True Comfort in Suffering, is <hi>demonſtrated</hi> to carry a <hi>Divine-Stamp,</hi> by begetting a <hi>ſecret</hi> Veneration in the very Hearts of ſuch, who <hi>Oppoſe</hi> the Truth.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in their Juſt Execution, never (I think) did <hi>win over</hi> any <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> to become a <hi>Patron</hi> for their Lies. The Reaſons are <hi>theſe:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Their Deluſive Joy ariſes, <hi>partly</hi> from <hi>fortifying</hi> and <hi>confirming</hi> themſelves with the Signe of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> as a <hi>Charm</hi> againſt the Fear of Death.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From a <hi>Popiſh Abſolution</hi> given <hi>before</hi> their Death: The <hi>Form of which,</hi> (as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel Sa</hi> reports) runs <hi>thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Paſſion <hi>of our Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>and the</hi> Merits <hi>of the moſt Bleſſed Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and of All the Saints, and of all thoſe</hi> Good Acts <hi>done by Thee,</hi> (we may interpret them for <hi>Exploits of Treaſon</hi>) <hi>and of all the</hi> Evil, <hi>which thou ſhalt patiently endure,</hi> (<hi>though</hi> juſtly <hi>for thy Crimes</hi>) ſerve, <hi>or be of Benefit unto thee, for the</hi> Remiſſion <hi>of all thy Sins, for</hi> Increaſe <hi>of Grace, and for the</hi> Reward <hi>of Eternal Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Their <hi>Falſe-forced</hi> Courage, flows from an Ambitious, <hi>Superſtitious Opinion,</hi> that their Super-abundant Sufferings, ſhall conſtitute a <hi>Stock or Treaſury of Merit,</hi> for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Indulgence to <hi>looſer</hi> Papiſts. For the <hi>like</hi> purpoſe, ſome <hi>Relicks</hi> of <hi>Pſeudo-Martyrs</hi> have been Buryed under an <hi>Altar,</hi> either to cry for <hi>Vengeance</hi> againſt their Unjuſt Judges, <hi>(Reputed ſuch by themſelves)</hi> or that every Maſs <hi>ſaid over ſuch an Altar,</hi> might Redeem a Soul out of <hi>Purgatory.</hi> So <hi>Ambitious</hi> are they, to <hi>ſhare</hi> and <hi>compeer</hi> with the Office of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, in making an <hi>All-ſufficient,</hi> and <hi>Meritorious Satisfaction</hi> for Sin: Yet, <hi>George Caſſander</hi> (in his Conſultation how to Reconcile <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi> in a <hi>Middle-Way</hi>) atteſts, That <hi>Saint Martin</hi> going to a Place in his <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> Famous for the <hi>Sepulchre</hi> of one who Dyed a <hi>Reputed Martyr,</hi> found out, that the People Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced and Adored the Relicks of a <hi>Wicked Thief.</hi> So dextrous are they, to put a <hi>Cheat</hi> upon the World, in boaſting of the Multitude of <hi>their Saints:</hi> Alſo, they ſet the Crown of Martyrdom on the Heads of <hi>Traytors,</hi> to whom the Merits of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Paſſion muſt be <hi>applyed</hi> for Abſolution, from all thoſe <hi>Impoſtures,</hi> which are ſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to <hi>All Right</hi> Sentiments of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here it may be <hi>Objected,</hi> that Proteſtants, do not profeſs, the <hi>True</hi> Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they look <hi>Dejected in</hi> their dying for it. To this I anſwer, that the <hi>Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, is not alway the true Herald</hi> of the <hi>Mind.</hi> Impreſſions of Divine Joy, uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at <hi>firſt,</hi> fill the Soul with <hi>Fear,</hi> leſt there ſhould be a <hi>Deluſion</hi> in its peace. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Real</hi> Martyrs, may not always Expreſs the Tranſport of Joy in ſuffering. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Rapture of Divines Joy, may ſo <hi>powerfully affect</hi> the Mind, that the Body may be Careleſs (in a manner) of Compoſing its <hi>Outward Mſpect, which</hi> Jeſuits
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98865:21"/>
                  <hi>more mind,</hi> in their <hi>Artificial</hi> Courage, than Sincerity to bear Teſtimony to the Truth. Yea, the Soul of a Real Martyr, may abate an <hi>Extrinſical</hi> Cheerfulneſs, by reaſon of the <hi>Indiſpoſition</hi> of the Body, which is incapable to bear <hi>Long</hi> the Exuberant Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Divine Joy. Yea the Soul <hi>It ſelf</hi> is ſomtimes hindred in a <hi>more diſtinct and deep</hi> Conſideration of thoſe divine Comforts which it poſſeſſes; becauſe it drinks In the Impreſſion of <hi>meanner</hi> Objects from the Senſes. Theſe <hi>flat and dead,</hi> the brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>pureſt Divineſt</hi> Conſolations, ſo that the ſtrength of its Joys may be <hi>Remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> upon this Account.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beſides</hi> the <hi>Spirituous</hi> Operation of them is deaded, by a dull <hi>Imperfect Deſcription</hi> of them unto <hi>Other Perſons,</hi> who cannot Conjecture, <hi>what</hi> they Are, by any Report made of them at the <hi>ſecond</hi> Hand. Thus, the Reflection of the Sun-beams, are <hi>Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> than the <hi>direct</hi> Influences: An Eccho is <hi>fainter</hi> in the Rebound, than the <hi>Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Articulation,</hi> or <hi>firſt Forming of the Voice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, Proteſtants ought not to <hi>Faint</hi> under Tribulation, becauſe Comfort doth not Spring up to them in an <hi>Extraordinary</hi> degree, as ſoon as they <hi>firſt</hi> ingage to give their Teſtimony to Chriſts pure Religion. It is not <hi>the part, or duty</hi> of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an under ſuffering, to <hi>Anticipate</hi> Divine Manifeſtations by Impatiency; nor to Carve the hidden <hi>Manna laviſhly,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſeaſonably</hi> to himſelf. It is Treaſured up, to be Revealed in the <hi>deepeſt</hi> extremities of ſuffering. The Spirit of Chriſt will not <hi>fail to Succour his Martyrs,</hi> in the <hi>Fitteſt</hi> Seaſon. For, He is not only a <hi>Prudent,</hi> but a <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> diſpenſer of his own Favours and Comforts.</p>
               <p>Let not therefore any Proteſtant <hi>Degenerate</hi> from an Holy courage and cheerfulneſs under his ſharpeſt Tryals. Let Him not <hi>Degrade</hi> himſelf below his Spiritual Dignity, by any puſillanimous warping in his Teſtimony to the Truths of Chriſt. We are to Count <hi>this,</hi> rather matter of great Joy, that we are <hi>Eſteemed</hi> by God, to be His Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Witneſſes, <hi>intruſted</hi> with the Defence of His pure Religion. If we <hi>Perſevere</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der His Banner, to overcome the Corruptions of Antichriſt, we ſhall at <hi>Laſt</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Robes</hi> of Glory, and <hi>Palms</hi> of Victory, as ſignal <hi>Trophies</hi> of our Eminent ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyal.</p>
               <p>Now, <hi>to wind up</hi> this whole Diſcourſe: If Jeſuits may expreſs an <hi>Artificial</hi> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity in ſuffering Exquiſite Torments for the Reputation of their <hi>falſe</hi> Religion; Then, let it be a ſeaſonable <hi>Caution,</hi> not to <hi>juſtify</hi> Impoſters, becauſe in their death, they may ſeem to <hi>parallel the</hi> real Zeal and Conſtancy of Proteſtants. <hi>Every Like is not the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, though ſome <hi>ſincere</hi> Martyrs, have ſeemed to <hi>ſet in a Cloud</hi> as not expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any <hi>Extraordinary</hi> Joys; yet, <hi>Suſpend</hi> your Cenſure of their Perſons, neither <hi>ſuſpect</hi> Chriſts pure Religion which they deſended: Their <hi>Grave</hi> Reſerved Seriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, was no diſhonourable <hi>Deſpondency.</hi> For, in the <hi>loweſt Ebb</hi> of Comfort, they were <hi>never deprived</hi> of a Lively Hope of Glory, which kept them <hi>Adhering</hi> to God in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, a <hi>Preſumptuous</hi> Sinner, a <hi>Cloſe</hi> Hypocrite, an <hi>Inſolent Self-deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Jeſuitical Impoſtor, may Counterfeit a <hi>Commendable</hi> Patience, <hi>Exceſſive</hi> Joy, and an <hi>Earneſt.</hi> Deſire to be Diſſolved. He may ſeem to Conflict with Death <hi>undaunted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and <hi>challenge</hi> an Executioner of Juſtice, <hi>to do his Worſt:</hi> And yet, all theſe <hi>Rays</hi> of Cheerfulneſs, and <hi>Raptures</hi> of Tranſporting Joy, may prove <hi>only</hi> the Preſumption of a <hi>deluded</hi> Conſcience.</p>
               <p>Therefore, ſet not the Crown of <hi>Martyrdom</hi> on the Heads of ſuch <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy Wretches.</hi> Give not <hi>ſuch</hi> the due <hi>Encomiums</hi> and Praiſes of <hi>Real</hi> Saints, who are only their <hi>Apes</hi> and <hi>Counterfeits</hi> in Life and Death. This would be to <hi>Juſtify</hi> the Wicked, which is an <hi>Abomination</hi> to the Lord. It will <hi>Harden</hi> Prophane Perſons. <hi>Incourage</hi> Hypocrites, and <hi>Sacrilegiouſly Rob the Saints</hi> of their due Honor and Veneration. Give not Prodigally a <hi>falſe</hi> Teſtimony to <hi>ſuch</hi> in their Death, who <hi>deſpiſed</hi> and <hi>oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> the Truths of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> (as <hi>Jeſuits</hi> do under the Title of His Society) or, who <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced</hi> the Ways of Holyneſs in their Lives.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Be not</hi> Deceived, <hi>God will not be</hi> Mockt: <hi>For, what any Man</hi> Sows, <hi>the very</hi> ſame <hi>ſhall he</hi> Reap<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. If to the Fleſh, <hi>Corruption,</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction</hi> ſhall be the Fruit of his <hi>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> Impiety</p>
               <p>Every Man's End is <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tually</hi> in his Way, or Courſe of Life. Reckon upon <hi>This,</hi> as an Eternal Truth, that <hi>Falſe and Licentious</hi> Principles, can never produce <hi>Solid,</hi> nor <hi>Laſting</hi> Comfort.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:98865:21"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
